<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Low Genit Tract Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Low Genit Tract Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2035</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">lwwopen</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JLGTD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Lower Genital Tract Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1089-2591</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1526-0976</issn><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name><meta-value>Lippincott Open Access</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11939099</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11939099.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11939099</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11939099</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39804372</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/LGT.0000000000000866</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JLGTD-2024-0064</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">JLGTD_240277</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" article-version-type="Version of Record">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>HPV Associated Disease: Guidelines and Guideline Discussion</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Updated Review for Guidelines for Cervical Cancer Screening in Immunosuppressed Women Without HIV Infection</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moscicki</surname><given-names initials="AB">Anna-Barbara</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0484-2742</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names initials="L">Lisa</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPH</degrees><email>lflowe2@emory.edu</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huchko</surname><given-names initials="MJ">Megan J.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPH</degrees><email>Megan.huchko@duke.edu</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8655-1764</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names initials="ME">Margaret E.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>Long.Margaret@mayo.edu</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacLaughlin</surname><given-names initials="KL">Kathy L.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>MacLaughlin.Kathy@mayo.edu</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names initials="J">Jeanne</given-names></name><degrees>PhD, CNM</degrees><email>jmurph60@jh.edu</email><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spiryda</surname><given-names initials="LB">Lisa Beth</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>lspiryda@obhg.com</email><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheckel</surname><given-names initials="CJ">Caleb J.</given-names></name><degrees>DO</degrees><email>Caleb.Scheckel@ocsri.org</email><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gold</surname><given-names initials="MA">Michael A.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>Michael.Gold@oscri.org</email><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics, University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, Emory University School of Medicine, Atlanta, GA</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Duke University School of Medicine, Durham, NC</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Family Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Gynecology and Obstetrics, Johns Hopkins Bayview Medical Center, Baltimore, MD</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>O7B Hospitalist Group and Department of Perinatal Services, HCA Florida St Lucie Hospital, Port, St. Lucie, FL</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Oklahoma Cancer Specialists and Research Institute, Tulsa, OK</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Oklahoma Tulsa, OU-TU School of Community Medicine, Tulsa, OK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corr1">Reprint requests to: Anna-Barbara Moscicki, MD, Department of Pediatrics, University of California, Los Angeles, 10833 Le Conte Ave MDCC 22-432, Los Angeles, CA 90095. E-mail: <email>Amoscicki@mednet.ucla.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">485281</issue-id><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>26</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-27 10:25:35.317"><day>27</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 The Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. on behalf of the ASCCP.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jlgtd-29-168.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jlgtd-29-168.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Objective</title><p>The purpose of this review was to examine new evidence since the authors' 2019 guidelines for cervical cancer (CC) screening in non-HIV immunocompromised persons and to provide updated recommendations based on literature review and expert opinion. In addition, human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccine efficacy in these populations was reviewed.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A literature search was performed similar to the authors' previous publication but was conducted through March 2023. Risk of CC, squamous intraepithelial lesions, and HPV infection in those living with solid organ transplant (SOT), end-stage renal disease (ESRD), hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT), and autoimmune diseases (AID), specifically systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), rheumatoid arthritis (RA), and inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) with addition of multiple sclerosis (MS) were researched. This update also summarizes data available on newer disease-modifying therapies (DMTs) including monoclonal antibodies (MABs). The authors then made recommendations for HPV vaccine administration, and screening using either general population guidelines or increased surveillance, the latter based on following current recommendations for women living with HIV. Additionally, the literature search included antibody response to HPV vaccines and recommendations for their administration for these same conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Based on the reviewed risks, evidence continued to support those persons living with SOT, ESRD, HSCT, and SLE, whether on immunosuppressant therapy or not, had an increased risk of HPV, squamous intraepithelial lesions, and CC whereas there was weak evidence that those persons with IBD, RA, and MS not on immunosuppressants were at risk. Data on persons using DMT/MAB were conflicting. Data showed that patients on certain immunosuppressants had lower antibody titers following HPV vaccination. There were no studies on HPV vaccine efficacy.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Following US Center for Disease Control and Prevention HIV Cervical cancer screening (CCS) guidelines is recommended for the following: SOT, ESRD, HSCT, and SLE whether on immunosuppressants or not, and IBD, RA, and MS on immunosuppressants. Shared decision-making about increased surveillance for IBD and RA not on immunosuppressants and persons on any DMT or MAB is reasonable based on conflicting data. Human papillomavirus vaccination should not change the recommendations for increased CC surveillance. A 3-dose series of the HPV vaccine is recommended for all age-eligible patients starting at 9 years of age, with catch-up to 26 years of age. Vaccination from age 27 up to age 45 years per Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices guidelines should be considered in shared decision-making. When possible, HPV vaccine series should be initiated and completed before SOT or initiation of DMT/MAB. For HSCT, the vaccine series should be readministered along with other childhood vaccines.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key Words</title><kwd>adult</kwd><kwd>female</kwd><kwd>humans</kwd><kwd>immunocompromised host</kwd><kwd>mass screening/methods*</kwd><kwd>middle aged</kwd><kwd>papillomavirus infections/diagnosis*</kwd><kwd>practice guidelines as topic</kwd><kwd>squamous intraepithelial lesions of the cervix/diagnosis*</kwd><kwd>uterine cervical neoplasms/diagnosis*</kwd><kwd>young adult</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>BACKGROUND</title><p>In 2019, we published American Society for Colposcopy and Cervical Pathology (ASCCP) guidelines for cervical cancer (CC) screening in immunocompromised women not infected with HIV.<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> Specifically, we evaluated those with solid organ transplant (SOT), hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT), and autoimmune diseases and provided recommendations for CC screening based on literature review and expert opinion. The rationale for the initial manuscript was to fill a gap in guidelines for these women as the US Center for Disease Control and Prevention's (CDC) guideline for CC screening for immunosuppressed women is specific to those living with HIV (see q4)&#8212;no other immunosuppressed group is included. As well, there is no international or national consensus on CC screening guidelines for non&#8211;HIV-immunosuppressed women.</p><p>Immunosuppression increases cervical and other HPV disease though impact varies with type and degree of immunosuppression. For example, SOT and HSCT recipients gain increased life expectancy and quality of life but at the cost of an increased risk of a spectrum of malignancies, mainly attributed to ongoing and long-term use of immunosuppressive medication, graft versus host disease (GVHD), and infections with oncogenic viruses. The risk of malignancy among patients with autoimmune disease is also of interest, both because of the disease pathogenesis and the increasing use of immunomodulatory therapy that may alter immunosurveillance. Based on the initial literature review, the authors concluded whether the risk of CC in the specific population of interest was greater or equal to the general population and if the risk was deemed greater, the recommendations were to follow the current US CDC guidelines for women living with HIV.<sup><xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> This existing pattern of increased surveillance/increased screening/enhanced screening was chosen if the condition indicated increased CC risk; there was no numerical risk-based evidence for other intervals and also effort to manage complexity of CC screening recommendations. The objective of this report is to update the review of the literature and to modify our original 2019 guidelines<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> if needed.</p><p>In this article, we review additional literature that was either not included or published after the 2019 ASCCP guidelines for the risks of CC, squamous intraepithelial lesions (SIL), and human papillomavirus (HPV) among 4 major groups of immunocompromised patients: those with (a) SOTs, (b) HSCT, (c) autoimmune diseases including systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), rheumatoid arthritis (RA), and inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), and new to this review (d) multiple sclerosis (MS). We also discuss the role of newer disease-modifying therapies (DMTs) including monoclonal antibodies (MABs). We then recommend CC screening for each of these groups based on this updated review and expert opinion and we underscore those populations who would or would not benefit from more frequent screening than the general population. Please refer to the original guidelines<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> for the previous literature review. Lastly, we review HPV vaccine immunogenicity in each of these groups.</p><p>Of note, the &#8220;2019 ASCCP Risk-Based Management Consensus Guidelines,<sup><xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>&#8221; published 1 year after our 2019 &#8220;Guidelines for Cervical Cancer Screening in Immunosuppressed Women Without HIV Infection<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>&#8221; aligned with our recommendation to screen all immunosuppressed patients according to the CDC guidelines for opportunistic infections that were published in 2018. In 2023, the original 2019 ASCCP Risk-Based Management Guidelines Committee, representing 19 national organizations, formally voted to endorse the updated 2021 CDC Opportunistic infection guidelines as the screening pattern for immunosuppressed individuals.<sup><xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> As the CDC document only refers to people living with HIV, this review will add to the evidence related to risks of CC among those living with other immunosuppressive conditions.</p><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Current Recommended Screening Strategies in Healthy Patients</title><p>Since the last guidelines, American Cancer Society (ACS) in 2020 updated their recommendations for CC screening in the general population.<sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Primary HPV screening is recommended starting at age 25 years. If negative, 5-year screening intervals are recommended. Alternatively, cotesting or cytology alone can be used with intervals of 5 and 3 years, respectively, also starting at 25 years of age. At the time this manuscript was written, ASCCP, American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (ACOG), and US Preventive Services Task Force (USPTF) continued to endorse the previous recommendations starting with cytology at 21 years of age and cotesting and primary HPV at 30 years of age. In part, ACS referenced several publications demonstrating the decrease in HPV vaccine types and abnormal cytology in the United States after the introduction of the HPV vaccine, and rates of girls receiving at least 1 vaccine dose are now above 50% for most states. In addition, ASCCP updated their management of abnormal CC screening tests based on a calculated risk of cervical intraepithelial neoplasia (CIN) 3+ from known databases and prespecified cut-offs for management (ie, close monitoring vs referral to colposcopy vs immediate treatment).<sup><xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Management is also based on knowledge of previous HPV test result when available. Screening intervals and management of abnormal CC screening tests are referred to the 2019 ASCCP guidelines which is a live, working document updated on regular intervals. Both the ACS and ASCCP emphasize that their guidelines are for the general population and not special populations such as the immunocompromised since there are no large databases that allow for risk-based screening or management in these populations. This is also true for the immunocompromised who have received the HPV vaccine since several studies have documented lower antibody titers in this populations.<sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> The efficacy of the vaccine in these immunosuppressed individuals&#8212;whether the vaccine was given before or after diagnosis&#8212;remains unknown.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><p>The expert panel conducting this updated review consisted of those initially involved in the creation of the 2019 guidelines<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> with the addition of a medical oncologist with knowledge of the new immunosuppressant agents commonly used. Literature searches were performed using 7&#8211;10 key words (ie, CC, cervical dysplasia/neoplasia/squamous intraepithelial lesion, human papillomavirus, HPV vaccine, and type of immunosuppression). Additional publications were identified from review of citations in these articles. All of the abstracts generated by the search were then reviewed to identify relevant articles. Reviews of the literature were summarized with relevant statistical comparisons. Confidence intervals are given if available.</p><p>Recommendations for screening generated from each group were largely based on expert opinion given limited available data. Consistent with the 2019 guidelines,<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> adherence to screening, health benefits and risks, and available clinical expertise were all considered in formulating the recommendations to the degree that this information was available. A formal cost-benefit analysis was not possible. Management of abnormal cytology and treatment strategies were not reviewed.</p><p>In this article, we propose that CC screening guidelines for immunocompromised patients without HIV infection either follow the (1) guidelines for the general population (ie, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://i.e.no" ext-link-type="uri">no</ext-link> strong evidence of increased risk of CIN 3 and CC) or (2) increase the frequency of screening based on the previous guidelines using the CDC guidelines for patients living with HIV (ie, evidence of increased risk of CIN 3 and CC). The latter will be referred to as &#8220;following the CDC HIV guidelines.<sup><xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>&#8221;</p><p>We also recognize that the guidelines for patients living with HIV are likely to change based on their increasing healthier status due to advancing therapies. In contrast, the immunosuppression of the non-HIV groups discussed here are primarily immunosuppressed therapeutically or iatrogenically. Consequently, we chose to endorse the current 2024 CDC guidelines even in the case that the HIV guidelines change to less frequent screening.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Solid Organ Transplant Recipients</title><p>Fourteen new articles fulfilled the criteria for full review. We also reviewed the literature from 2013 to 2021 to address three new areas: SOT in pediatric patients (2 articles), CC/SIL risk in those with End-Stage Renal Disease (ESRD)/Dialysis (4 articles), and HPV vaccination in female (assigned at birth) SOT patients (5 articles).</p><sec><title>Human Papillomavirus</title><p>Since our last review, 2 studies confirmed increased HPV prevalence and acquisition of HPV after SOT.<sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> The larger of the two was a cross-sectional observational study comparing 125 patients with SOTs (68 kidney, 4 kidney and pancreas, 28 liver, 17 lung, and 8 heart) to 132 immunocompetent controls. There was an increased frequency of cervical hrHPV types seen in the SOT recipients (19.4% vs 7.9%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .014).<sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Squamous Intraepithelial Lesions</title><p>Since 2019, there were 3 additional studies reaffirming the increased risk of SIL in SOT patients.<sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Two studies,<sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> both of which did not stratify types of SOT, showed increased LSIL and HSIL in SOT recipients. The larger cross-sectional study showed that within 5.5 years of transplant, SOT recipients had higher rate of SIL when compared to controls (15% vs 2.4%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001).<sup><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Although no statistical comparisons were made, HSIL alone was noted to be higher as well (5.3% vs 0.8%, respectively).</p><p>Reinholdt et al.,<sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> specifically examined the age at time of renal transplant and subsequent development of CIN 2,3 within 20 years of transplant compared to randomly selected, age-matched controls from the Danish registry over the time period 1990&#8211;2015: 4,261 renal transplant patients and 212,673 control patients.<sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Renal transplant patients had an increased hazard ratio of 2.1 (95% confidence interval [CI] = 1.7&#8211;2.8) for CIN 2,3 as compared to controls. When the cumulative incidence of SIL was examined longitudinally, patients &lt;30 years of age at time of transplant had higher incidence of CIN within 20 years when compared to those who were aged 30&#8211;39 at time of transplant (15% [95% CI = 10%&#8211;21%] vs 10% [95% CI = 6%&#8211;15%]); both groups had greater than the 4%&#8211;8% risk of CIN 2,3 when compared to the control group. Those with a functioning renal graft, implying adherence to immunosuppressive medications, had an increased adjusted hazard ratio for CIN 2,3 of 2.3 (95% CI = 1.8&#8211;3.0) compared to the control population.<sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Of note, guidelines from the American Society of Transplantation Infectious Diseases Community of Practice stated that every 6-month cytology for 1 year after management of acute rejection, especially with antilymphocyte agents, might be reasonable; no definitive data regarding risk of SIL after treatment of acute rejection was identified.<sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Cervical cancer</title><p>The one additional publication examining rates of CC after an SOT was a large cohort study utilizing nationwide registry data. Renal transplant patients compared to control patients had an increased CC risk (hazard ratio = 2.8; 95% CI = 1.4&#8211;5.4).<sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Overall HPV vaccination rates were low at about 2% in both the renal transplant and control groups. <sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Childhood and Adolescent SOT and Risk of HPV, SIL, CIN, and CC</title><p>There have been limited data published on HPV, SIL, and CC risks following SOT in pediatric and adolescent patients. Given the advances in SOT, many childhood SOT recipients have longer life expectancies allowing them to benefit from health screenings. One retrospective study examined posttransplant malignancies in 884 females (assigned at birth) with a renal transplant that occurred between the ages of 0 and 17 years; three with cervical adenocarcinomas (0.3%) during a median follow-up of 19.6 years (interquartile range [IQR] = 9.3&#8211;29.8)<sup><xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> were identified, which would be higher than expected based on SEER data for the same time period.<sup><xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The second study, based on registry data, showed the incidence rate for CC was 1.7 per 10,000<sup><xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> in females (assigned at birth) younger than 18 years old at transplant with a standardized incidence rate ratio (SIR) of 11 (95% CI = 0.3&#8211;61.2).<sup><xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Risk Factors for Abnormal Cervical Cytology Prior to Transplant in ESRD: Risk of HPV, SIL, CIN, and CC in ESRD</title><p>Patients with ESRD on dialysis prerenal transplant are another immunosuppressive group with increased risk of HPV, SIL, and CC.<sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> End-stage renal disease was associated with an increased risk of CC with an incident rate ratio (IRR) of 1.81 (95% CI = 1.01&#8211;3.23) compared to controls in a prospective registry dataset.<sup><xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> United States registry data showed an additional increased risk of CC the more years with ESRD on dialysis; specifically, the IR of CC in 6 years went from 48.9/100,000 in ESRD patients (general population IR of 7.9/100,000) to an IR in the ESRD population of 117.7/100,000 (general population IR of 7.0/100,000).<sup><xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Another study showed that the odds ratio (OR) for CC increased by 1.18 (95% CI = 1&#8211;1.38) for every 10% decrease in estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR).<sup><xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup></p><p>Several risk factors have been associated with increased abnormal cytology and CC in ESRD/dialysis patients including: autoimmune chronic kidney disease (OR = 2.71), age less than 50 years (OR = 1.68), and history of prior kidney transplant (OR = 2.64).<sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Lastly, when comparing patients on dialysis to those with a functioning renal transplant, the incident rates (IR) for CC were 55.9 (95% CI = 28.0&#8211;112) and 46.3 (95% CI = 17.4&#8211;123), respectively, demonstrating that the rates of CC were similar.<sup><xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec><title>Human Papillomavirus Vaccine Immunogenicity</title><p>Published studies in both pediatric/adolescent and adult populations with SOTs have no major adverse safety events other than injection site reactions. Seroconversion ranged from 45% to 72% depending upon HPV type, type of transplant, and immunosuppressive medication profile.<sup><xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> A Belgian study assessed seroconversion following nonavalent HPV vaccine administration in SOT recipients (56 renal, 57 heart, 58 lung) over a 7-month period; the mean age was 42 years, ranging from 18 to 55 years.<sup><xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Overall seroconversion rates for all SOT patients were 64.3% (95% CI = 55.8%&#8211;72.2%) for HPV 6, 70.7% (95% CI = 62.7%&#8211;77.8%) for HPV 11, 69.1% (95% CI = 61.0%&#8211;76.4%) for HPV 16, 51.7% (95% CI = 43.2%&#8211;60.2%) for HPV 18, 55.9% (95% CI = 47.6%&#8211;64.0%) for HPV 31, 66.9% (95% CI = 58.8%&#8211;74.3%) for HPV 33, 46.0% (95% CI = 37.8%&#8211;54.3%) for HPV 45, 65.3% (95% CI = 57.1%&#8211;72.9%) for HPV 52, and 72.0% (95% CI = 64.1%&#8211;79.0%) for HPV 58. Seroconversion rates were lowest in lung SOT recipients likely due to the intensity of the immunosuppressive medication regimen, and those receiving mycophenolate mofetil or tacrolimus.<sup><xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> Additionally, seroconversion to at least 1 covered HPV type was higher with the full 3-series vaccine course (76.3%; 95% CI = 62.8%&#8211;89.8%) than with 1 or 2 vaccines only (61.7%; 95% CI = 47.8%&#8211;75.6%). Other studies have corroborated these differences in seroconversion.<sup><xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Immunogenicity of HPV vaccine tended to be lower for vaccination a year or less after SOT compared to more than a year after (OR = 0.21; 95% CI = 0.04%&#8211;1.03%).<sup><xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Improvements in immunogenicity with delayed vaccination need to be weighed against risk of new HPV exposure while awaiting vaccination.</p><p>In adolescent populations receiving SOTs,<sup><xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> seropositivity rates were 100% in the liver transplant recipients and 50%&#8211;75% (depending on HPV type) in the kidney transplant recipients; of note, the kidney transplant recipients were on multiple immunosuppressive agents and the liver transplant patients were only on a single agent.<sup><xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> Immunogenicity of HPV vaccine has also been compared in adolescents with chronic kidney disease (CKD), dialysis dependence, or kidney transplant<sup><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup>; at 12 months postvaccination, antibody response was 100% for all 4 HPV genotypes in the chronic kidney disease/dialysis group, whereas in the transplant patients, seropositivity at 12 months was 62.5% for HPV 6 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .02), 50% for HPV 11 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001), 75% for HPV 16 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .04), and 50% for HPV 18 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .001).<sup><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> Vaccination did not appear to impact the rate of rejection.<sup><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup></p><p>One study attempted to evaluate the efficacy of catch-up HPV vaccination for ages 18&#8211;26 years to reduce rates of CIN2+ in immunosuppressed individuals (HIV infection, organ transplant recipients, systemic immunosuppressive medication use<sup><xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup>). Those with 1 or more HPV vaccine doses were compared to those with no HPV vaccination with an relative risk (RR) for CIN2+ of 1.00 (95% CI = 0.71&#8211;1.42) and for CIN3+ of 1.02 (95% CI = 0.58&#8211;1.80). For nonimmunocompromised individuals, catch-up vaccine reduced CIN 2+ by 19% and in immunosuppressed by 4%.</p><p>The American Society of Transplantation Infectious Diseases Community of Practice published vaccination guidelines for SOT recipients.<sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Optimally, HPV vaccination should be completed prior to transplantation according to established guidelines for the general population given the reduced immunogenicity following SOT. If the complete series has not been administered prior to SOT, recipients should resume the vaccination schedule 3&#8211;6 months posttransplant<sup><xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> or initiate it a year posttransplant.<sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> Persons of all ages should get a 3-vaccine course.<sup><xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Timing for initiation of HPV vaccine after SOT requires balancing improved immunogenicity with delay versus risk of new HPV exposure while waiting.</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Summary for HPV, SIL, CIN, and CC Risk in Patients With SOT and ESRD.</title><p>This updated review continues to show an elevated risk of HPV, SIL, and CC among patients with SOT and also now includes patients with ESRD on renal dialysis. Recommendations endorse following the CDC HIV guidelines in SOT and ESRD patients. A 3-dose HPV vaccination series should be offered at the recommended ages (ie, age 9 through 26 years with shared decision-making for those age 27 through 45 years). For SOT, HPV vaccine strategies should follow the American Society of Transplantation Infectious Diseases Community of Practice described above. Solid organ transplant is associated with an increased risk of vulvar, anal, and vaginal cancer in addition to CC. Additionally, ESRD is associated with an increased risk of vulvar cancer.<sup><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> These risks should be considered when providing gynecologic care.</p></sec><sec><title>Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</title><p>Two published articles were found to fulfill the criteria for review. There were no new studies of HPV and SIL risk post-HSCT between 2018 and 2022 that fit the criteria for inclusion.</p><p>We identified 1 article from 2013 to 2021 evaluating HPV vaccine immunogenicity in female (assigned at birth) HSCT patients, a topic not addressed in our previously published guideline.<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p><sec><title>Cervical Cancer</title><p>A SEER/Medicare-based, retrospective, case-control study of 700 cases with hematologic malignancies and HSCT were matched 1:5 with 3,159 controls who did not undergo HSCT. In addition, a random sample of 5% of noncancer controls were matched to cases 5:1. Outcomes included any HPV-related genital cancers in the cervix, vagina, or vulva combined. Results showed that the proportion of HPV-related precancer or second malignancy was higher in HSCT patients than in noncancer controls (4.8% vs 1.4%, OR = 3.49; 95% CI = 1.69&#8211;7.20). Also, while chronic GVHD was included as a covariate, genital chronic GVHD was not available in the dataset and was not included as a covariate in the analysis.<sup><xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup></p><p>In a Korean study of cancer incidence in allogeneic HSCT patients, 10,354 patients were matched 1:1 with noncancer patients.<sup><xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> There was an increased risk of all gynecologic cancers at 10 years (HR = 2.69, 95% CI = 1.04&#8211;6.96, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .041). Limitations of this study included that CC was not separated out from other gynecologic cancers and was not characterized as HPV-related. In addition, GVHD comorbidity was not measured.<sup><xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></p><sec><title>Human Papillomavirus Vaccine Immunogenicity</title><p>There was 1 study of the safety and immunogenicity of quadrivalent HPV vaccine after allogeneic HSCT in female (assigned at birth) patients ages 18&#8211;50 years in a single-arm nonrandomized clinical trial at the National Institutes of Health.<sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Patients and healthy controls received a 3-dose series of quadrivalent HPV vaccine. Assays for anti&#8211;HPV 6-, 11-, 16-, and 18-specific antibody levels were drawn prior to vaccination and at 2, 6, 7, and 12 months after receiving the first injection. Results showed that 18 of 23 patients receiving immunosuppression (78.3%), 20 of 21 (95.2%) not receiving immunosuppression, and all 20 healthy volunteers developed antibodies to all the HPV types present in the vaccine (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .04). At both months 7 and 12, the change in HPV antibody levels from baseline was not significantly different between the 2 posttransplant groups, or between either the posttransplant group or the healthy group (Kruskal-Wallis test; all <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; .05).</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Summary of HPV, SIL CIN, and CC Screening in Patients With History of HSCT</title><p>This updated review continues to show an elevated risk of CC among patients with HSCT whether on immunosuppression or not. There was no new information on those with a new diagnosis of genital or chronic GVHD; however, previous data suggested increased risk for HSIL or CC for this group of patients. Recommendations endorse following the CDC HIV guidelines for screening for patients with HSCT and new diagnosis of genital and chronic GVH. A 3-dose HPV vaccination series should be offered at the recommended ages.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</title><p>Nine articles were found to fulfill the criteria for full review. We included 1 article from 2013 evaluating HPV vaccine immunogenicity in female IBD patients, a topic not addressed in our previously published guideline.<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p><sec><title>Human Papillomavirus</title><p>At a hospital-based IBD Clinic in China, HPV detection prevalence in 124 IBD patients (94 with Crohn disease, 30 with ulcerative colitis) was compared to 372 controls.<sup><xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> There was no difference in overall HPV positivity between IBD patients and controls [OR = 1.63 (95% CI = 0.87&#8211;3.05)], but IBD patients were at increased risk of infection with HPV 16/18 genotypes [OR = 29.0 (95% CI = 3.64&#8211;211.0)]. Higher odds of HPV detection were observed in IBD patients on methotrexate [OR = 4.76 (95% CI = 1.47&#8211;15.4), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .005] and in those treated with 3 or more immunosuppressants [OR = 3.64 (95% CI = 1.25&#8211;10.6), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .013].<sup><xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Squamous Intraepithelial Lesion and Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</title><p>In a retrospective cohort study from Australia, compared with controls, 2,683 patients with IBD had higher rates of low-grade cytologic abnormalities [adjusted hazard ratio (AHR) = 1.19 (95% CI = 1.09&#8211;1.29)] but no significant difference in high-grade cytologic abnormalities [AHR = 1.12 (95% CI = 0.96&#8211;1.29)] or high-grade histology, defined as CIN2+ [AHR = 1.02 (95% CI = 0.85&#8211;1.24)]. Use of immunosuppressant medication was not considered in the analysis.<sup><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> In a study of 99 German patients with IBD, only low-grade cytologic abnormalities were significantly more prevalent in 65 IBD patients on immunosuppressive therapy than in 550 healthy controls [OR = 4.96 (95% CI = 2.73&#8211;9.02)].<sup><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Cervical Cancer</title><p>In a retrospective review of national datasets in England, 36,673 patients with CC were identified and, among them, 352 had IBD. Age-standardized rates showed a higher CC rate in patients with IBD (5.2 per 100,000) compared with non-IBD patients (4.6 per 100,000; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .042). The impact of immunosuppressant medication use was not evaluated.<sup><xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup></p><p>A population-based study using a South Korean insurance claims database compared CC incidence in 12,632 patients with ulcerative colitis to 36,797 age-matched controls. Although there was no difference in likelihood of CC overall [aHR = 1.56 (95% CI = 0.97&#8211;2.50)] with stratification by age, patients &#8805;60 years old with ulcerative colitis had higher likelihood of CC than controls [aHR = 3.65 (95% CI = 1.54&#8211;8.66)]. There was no difference in CC rates among patients with ulcerative colitis associated with the use of immunosuppressive medications.<sup><xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup></p><p>A multicenter Dutch cohort showed a higher detection rate of CIN2 + (included CC) [standardized detection rate (SDR) = 1.27 (95% CI = 1.05&#8211;1.52)] among 2,098 patients with IBD compared with 8,379 age-matched controls as well as a greater risk of developing CIN2+ over the study time [IRR = 1.66 (95% CI = 1.21&#8211;2.25)].<sup><xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> The individual detection rates for CIN2, CIN3, and CC was due to CIN2 rates alone, and specifically among those aged 35&#8211;44 years old. The longitudinal risk over time of developing CIN2+ was due to the combined effect of an increased risk of CIN2 and CIN3 but not of CC. An association was not observed between CIN2+ risk and history of immunomodulator or biologic treatment.<sup><xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup></p><p>Using the Dutch IBD biobank and a national registry, a retrospective cohort study including 1,318 patients with Crohn disease and 663 with ulcerative colitis found that 99 cases of CIN 2+ were diagnosed over a median follow-up of 17.2 years. There was no association between ever versus never use of the immunosuppressive medications studied and development of CIN2+.<sup><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup></p><p>A meta-analysis of 7 cohort studies with 94,144 IBD patients and 53,661,004 controls and 4 case-control studies with 20,267 IBD patients and 60,034 controls published between 2006 and 2019 found no association between IBD and risk of CC [OR/RR = 1.54 (95% CI = 0.83&#8211;2.85).<sup><xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> A significant association was observed between IBD and risk of noncancerous cervical abnormalities [OR/RR = 2.46 (95% CI = 1.55&#8211;3.91)]. There was no analysis by immunosuppressive therapy status.<sup><xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup></p><p>In a meta-analysis of 5 population-based cohort studies published between 2001 and 2021 including 74,310 patients with IBD and 2,029,087 controls, there was no significant increase in CC risk among IBD patients [HR = 1.24 (95% CI = 0.94&#8211;1.63).<sup><xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup> There was no observed difference in CC risk assessed by IBD type for ulcerative colitis or Crohn disease. Subgroup analysis of the studies that included data on cervical neoplasia showed higher risk of LSIL [HR = 1.15 (95% CI = 1.04&#8211;1.28)] but not of HSIL [HR = 1.36 (95% CI = 0.97&#8211;1.90)] in those with IBD (Mann 2022).<sup><xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Human Papillomavirus Vaccine Immunogenicity</title><p>We identified one study reporting on immunogenicity of HPV vaccination for patients with IBD on an immunosuppressant medication (tumor necrosis factor [TNF]-alpha inhibitor or immunomodulator) for a minimum of 1 month before enrollment.<sup><xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> In the prospective cohort study of 37 females aged 9&#8211;26 years with IBD, 33 completed the 3-dose quadrivalent HPV vaccination series with seropositivity of 100% to HPV types 6, 11, and 16, and 94% seropositivity to HPV 18 in testing 2&#8211;6 weeks after the final vaccine dose. Geometric mean titer levels were similar to historic controls without IBD.<sup><xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup></p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Summary of HPV, SIL, and CC Risk for Patients With Inflammatory Bowel Disease</title><p>This updated review continues to shows an increased risk for HPV and SIL, but conflicting evidence about CC risk in patients with IBD on immunosuppressive therapy. Recommendations endorse following the CDC HIV guidelines for screening in IBD patients on immunosuppressive therapy given the lack of definitive association with CC may reflect more intense screening and treatment of precancer in the populations studied. The evidence on patients not on immunosuppressive therapy is conflicting mostly because studies often lacked immunosuppressive therapy use and no additional recommendations are made than for the general population with an option for shared decision-making. A 3-dose HPV vaccination series should be offered at the recommended ages.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</title><p>Seven articles were found to fulfill the criteria for review. We included 6 articles from 2013 to 2021 evaluating HPV vaccine immunogenicity in female (assigned at birth) SLE patients.</p><sec><title>Human Papillomavirus</title><p>In a meta-analysis of 9 cross-sectional studies including 751 patients with SLE and 5,144 controls, cervical HPV detection (pooled prevalence in random effects meta-analysis) in patients with SLE was 34.15% (95% CI = 19.6%&#8211;52.5%) compared with 15.3% (95% CI = 0.79%&#8211;27.8%) in controls [OR = 2.87 (95% CI = 2.20&#8211;3.76), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; .0001].<sup><xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> There was no difference in HPV detection prevalence among SLE patients by immunosuppressive therapy status. Four studies looked specifically at the impact of azathioprine or cyclophosphamide on HPV detection prevalence in patients with SLE compared with no immunosuppressant and also found no difference.<sup><xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Squamous Intraepithelial Lesions and Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</title><p>In a retrospective cohort study from Australia, 702 patients with SLE or Mixed Connective Tissue Disease (MCTD) were compared to 985,583 female (assigned at birth) controls. Patients with SLE/Mixed Connective Tissue Disease had higher rates of high-grade histology (5.57 vs 3.76 per 1,000 person-years, AHR = 1.47, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .033).<sup><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Cervical Cancer</title><p>A prospective cohort study from China followed 8,120 patients with autoimmune diseases over 38,727 person-years between January 2006 and April 2015.<sup><xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> Patients with SLE had a standardized incidence ratio (SIR) for CC of 5.38 (95% CI = 1.97&#8211;11.71).<sup><xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> A retrospective cohort analysis of the Korean National Health Insurance Claims database reviewed claims between 2008 and 2014.<sup><xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup> A total of 21,016 patients with SLE were compared to 105,080 age- and sex-matched controls. The SIR for CC among patients with SLE was 3.09&#8211;3.22 (95% CI = 2.30&#8211;4.26).<sup><xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup></p><p>In a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective studies, 48 cohort studies involving 247,575 patients to assess cancer risk and cancer mortality among SLE patients were included.<sup><xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Among the 20 prospective cohort studies looking at CC risk, the CC risk was higher among patients with SLE (RR = 2.17, 95% CI = 1.53&#8211;3.07).<sup><xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> This study updates a prior meta-analysis from the same group that included articles that were not restricted to prospective cohort studies. That paper, published in 2018, showed an increased risk of CC among patients with SLE (SIR = 1.56, 95% CI = 1.29&#8211;1.88) across 11 included studies.<sup><xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> Another systematic review and meta-analysis found a similar increased relative risk of 1.66 (95% CI = 1.16&#8211;2.36) for CC across 14 studies and 103,845 participants.<sup><xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Human Papillomavirus Vaccine Immunogenicity</title><p>Multiple small prospective studies have reported satisfactory immunogenicity and safety with the quadrivalent HPV vaccine series (4vHPV) for patients with SLE. Among 16 females aged 12&#8211;26 years old with SLE with baseline seronegative status who completed the 3-dose 4vHPV series, seropositivity was &gt;94% for all HPV types in all but 1 subject who had received rituximab during the vaccine series.<sup><xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> Another study reported 100% seroconversion for all HPV types after the 3-dose 4vHPV series among 34 participants aged 19&#8211;50 years old with minimally active or inactive SLE.<sup><xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref></sup></p><p>A multicenter prospective study evaluated the 4vHPV vaccine as a 2- (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 30) or 3-dose series (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 180) in 9- to 20-year-old females with SLE. The 2-dose group had 93% seropositivity to HPV 16 and 83% to HPV 18 compared with 97% and 91%, respectively, to HPV 16 and 18 in the 3-dose group. Healthy controls (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 35) received the 3-dose series and had 100% seroconversion to HPV 16 and 18.<sup><xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup>One study reported on antibody response to a 3-dose 4vHPV vaccine series in 50 patients aged 18&#8211;35 years old with stable SLE, most on an immunomodulator, compared with healthy controls.<sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> At 7 months after vaccine series initiation, seroconversion from a negative baseline for HPV 16 was 92% for patients with SLE versus 98% for controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .34), and for HPV 18 was 76% for patients with SLE versus 93% for controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .06).<sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> In a follow-up study 5 years later, seropositivity to HPV 16 persisted in 94% and to HPV 18 in 96% in the SLE group compared with 100% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .49) and 96% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 1.0) among the control group.<sup><xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup> A meta-analysis of 6 studies reported pooled seroconversion rates for SLE patients at 7 months after 3-dose HPV vaccine series initiation for HPV 16 as 96.4% (95% CI = 0.93&#8211;1.00) and for HPV 18 as 91.8% (95% CI = 0.85&#8211;1.00).<sup><xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup></p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Summary of HPV, SIL CIN, and CC Screening in Patients With Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</title><p>This updated review continues to show an elevated risk of HPV, SIL, and CC among patients with SLE whether on immunosuppressants or not. Recommendations endorse following the CDC HIV guidelines for CC screening with or without immunosuppressant use and 3-dose HPV vaccination series should be offered at the recommended ages.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Rheumatoid Arthritis</title><p>Three articles published since the 2019 guidelines were found to fulfill the criteria for review. We did not identify any articles evaluating HPV detection risk after the prior guidelines were developed, nor any that investigate vaccine immunogenicity in adult female RA patients. We identified 2 studies that looked at these outcomes among adolescents with Juvenile Idiopathic Arthritis (JIA), which we included as a proxy for a similar disease process in a vaccine-eligible population.</p><sec><title>Squamous Intraepithelial Lesions and Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</title><p>Two of the studies examined the risk of SIL among women with RA, and found no increased risk. One of the studies was retrospective comparing 1,426 patients with RA to 985,583 female controls.<sup><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> Use of immunosuppressants was not addressed in this study. The second was a prospective cohort study that examined the association of biologic therapy with rates of CIN and found no statistically significant differences in rates of high-grade CIN between patients exposed to biologic Disease-Modifying Therapies (b-DMTs) compared to b-DMT&#8211;naive patients (1.3% vs 1.0%, 95% CI = &#8722;2&#8211;10).<sup><xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Cervical Cancer</title><p>The study referred to above in Chinese patients with autoimmune diseases<sup><xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup> showed that patients with RA had an SIR of 9.50 (95% CI = 4.91&#8211;16.59) for CC. No data were given on use of immunosuppressants.</p></sec><sec><title>Human Papillomavirus Vaccine Immunogenicity</title><p>Two prospective studies showed safety and immunogenicity of the 3-dose bivalent vaccine among adolescent females with JIA was no different from what was observed among healthy females after 3 doses. The numbers of JIA patients on methotrexate or TNF inhibitors was too small to observe any effect of medication.<sup><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup> In both studies, there were similar rates of local reactions to the vaccine and no difference in JIA disease progression.</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Summary of Risk of HPV, SIL, CIN, and CC Screening in Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis</title><p>This updated review continues to show an increased risk for HPV, SIL, and CC in patients with RA on immunosuppressive therapy. Recommendations endorse following the CDC HIV guidelines for CC screening for patients with RA on immunosuppressive therapy. The data on patients not on immunosuppressive therapy continue to be conflicting but studies often did not include the status of immunosuppressant use and therefore, recommendations are no different than the general population with an option for shared decision-making. A 3-dose HPV vaccination series should be offered at the recommended ages for all patients.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Multiple Sclerosis</title><p>We identified 38 articles that examined the relationship between MS and HPV, SIL, and CC. As this topic was not reviewed for the last publication, articles were reviewed beginning in 2000.</p><sec><title>Human Papillomavirus</title><p>Only 1 study analyzed the risk of HPV in individuals with MS. An analysis of electronic health records at Vanderbilt University demonstrated no impact of MS on the incidence of HPV positivity in a case-control study, although the percentage of those with HPV was extremely low (0.4% of cases vs 0.2% of controls).<sup><xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref></sup></p></sec><sec><title>Squamous Intraepithelial Lesion and Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</title><p>A retrospective observational cohort study in Australia included 1,426 patients with MS.<sup><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> They found no increase in the incidence of SIL, although there were some significant differences between patients with MS and controls, including the number of cytology tests performed. The impact of DMTs was not evaluated. A registry-based cohort study in Sweden compared MS patients on fingolimod, natalizumab, and rituximab to the general population.<sup><xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref></sup> Although follow-up was only 2&#8211;4 years depending upon the cohort, no difference in hazard ratio was seen for natalizumab (1.29; 95% CI = 0.71&#8211;2.34) or rituximab (1.15; 95% CI = 0.66&#8211;2.02). A numerical, but not statistical, increase was seen in association with fingolimod (1.63; 95% CI = 0.94&#8211;2.82), which was similar to the overall risk of developing any cancer while on fingolimod (1.53; 95% CI = 0.98&#8211;2.38).</p></sec><sec><title>Cervical Cancer</title><p>A population-based registry study was performed linking information from the Danish Multiple Sclerosis Register and the Danish Cancer Register.<sup><xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref></sup> Overall, 1,037 cancers were observed in 11,817 patients with MS. The overall cancer risk, and the risk of CC specifically, were similar between cases and controls (40 cases of CC compared to an expected 36.05 cases; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 1.11 [0.81&#8211;1.41]). Another Danish Registry study also evaluated patients with MS and, among 14,403 patients, demonstrated similar CC risk to that of the general population (SIR = 1.2; 95% CI = 0.9&#8211;1.6).<sup><xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> Another study examined 1,218 female (assigned at birth) Swedish patients with MS in a case-control series and reported no difference in risk of CC (HR = 0.83; 95% CI = 0.64&#8211;1.07) (Bahmanyar 2009).<sup><xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref></sup> Another Swedish study also found no difference in CC risk between cases and controls (SIR = 0.92; 95% CI = 0.54&#8211;1.45).<sup><xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></sup> This study also found no difference in the risk of death from CC (HR = 1.81; 95% CI = 0.91&#8211;3.62). A linked abstraction of hospital and mortality data from the UK included 2,812 patients with MS.<sup><xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref></sup> No change in incidence of CC was seen either before the diagnosis (ARR = 0.8; 95% CI = 0.3&#8211;1.7) or after the diagnosis (ARR = 1.3; 95% CI = 0.5&#8211;2.8) of MS. Three other studies identified no difference in the risk of CC among MS patients compared to the general population.<sup><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref></sup> Use of DMTs was not included in these studies.</p><p>A registry-based study compared 6,949 Norwegian MS patients to 37,922 patients in the general population during the time periods of 1953&#8211;1995 (before the introduction of DMTs) and 1996&#8211;2017 (after the introduction).<sup><xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref></sup> The earlier cohort demonstrated a similar incidence rate ratio of both overall cancer (IRR = 1.11; 95% CI = 0.90&#8211;1.37) and female (assigned at birth) genital organ cancer (IRR = 0.78; 95% CI = 0.48&#8211;1.27). In the latter cohort, the overall incidence rate ratio of cancer was higher among those with MS (IRR = 1.38; 95% CI = 1.28&#8211;1.52). The incidence rate ratio for female (assigned at birth) genital organ cancer was also increased (IRR = 1.40; 95% CI = 1.09&#8211;1.80). The authors concluded that the use of DMTs increased the risk of cancer among patients with MS. An obvious limitation of this study, however, is that it did not separate out CC from other female (assigned at birth) genital organ cancers&#8212;although this would also include other cancers such as vaginal and vulvar cancer, which may also be HPV-related and are rarer than CC. A similar analysis performed evaluated MS patients and matched controls in Ontario, Canada, during the years 1998&#8211;2007 and 2008&#8211;2017.<sup><xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref></sup> Age-standardized incident rates of CC were no different from the general population in either time cohort [1998&#8211;2007 (IRR = 0.92 (95% CI = 0.52&#8211;1.63)] and 2008&#8211;2017 [IRR = 0.84 (95% CI = 0.53&#8211;1.33)]. There were no data on the use of DMTs.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>HPV Vaccine Immunogenicity</title><p>There were no available data on the efficacy of HPV vaccination in patients with MS. In general, inactivated (nonlive) vaccines can be safely administered in patients with MS regardless of their concomitant use of immunologic therapies. Additionally, routine vaccination with inactivated vaccines is not associated with an increase in risk of MS relapse.<sup><xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref></sup></p><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Summary of Risk of HPV, SIL, CIN, and CC Screening in Patients With MS</title><p>This review on MS is new to the CC screening guidelines on non&#8211;HIV-immunosuppressed patients. There is no strong evidence to support that MS alone increases cervical SIL or CC risk. In contrast, immunosuppressant or DMT (see below) does seem to increase the risk, although results are conflicting regarding the risk associated with individual DMTs. The lack of association with CC risk may also be due to the intense screening in patients with MS, which would have led to enhanced detection and treatment of preinvasive lesions. We conclude that MS patients not on immunosuppressive treatment have no greater risk than the general population and those on immunosuppressive treatment may reflect a greater risk of CC than the general population. The recommendation for CC screening of patients with MS on immunosuppressive therapy should follow the CDC HIV CC screening guidelines; the recommendation for patients not on immunosuppressive therapy should follow CC screening guidelines for the general population with an option for shared-decision making. A 3-dose HPV vaccination series should be offered at the recommended ages for all patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Disease Modifying Therapies Including Monoclonal Antibodies</title><p>The increased use of DMTs in the treatment of autoimmune diseases and hematologic malignancies have improved disease-specific outcomes but can be associated with B-cell depletion, secondary hypogammaglobulinemia via plasma cell depletion, and heightened risk for viral infection. These therapies may also result in T-cell inactivation, cytokine modulation, and altered immunosurveillance of malignancy. Together, these effects could theoretically inhibit HPV viral clearance and promote CC progression (reviewed below in detail). Few publications have adequately addressed these risks, however, and individual study results demonstrate a mixed impact, secondary to methodological flaws. Limitations have included combining patients on different therapies that have varying mechanisms of action and therefore varying risk profiles, inclusion of patients on agents that are no longer in use, inclusion of patients who have changed therapies throughout the study, and short overall follow-up. Additionally, because of the rarity of CC in Western countries, many studies have looked at the combined risk of multiple malignancies including CC. It is therefore impossible to compile a complete list of DMTs or to pinpoint the impact that any individual drug may have on HPV persistence or the development of high-grade cervical neoplasia or CC. What follows is a brief review of the available data.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Disease-Modifying Therapies in General</title><p>No studies have specifically addressed the risk of DMTs and HPV infection. Two studies evaluated the risk of progression of cervical neoplasia to cancer in patients receiving DMTs. The first study reported on 951 patients with spondyloarthritis followed for 9.2 &#177; 5.9 years, 34 of whom developed cervical neoplasia (including both SIL and CC).<sup><xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref></sup> Neither the risk of developing cervical neoplasia nor the risk of progression of SIL to CC were related to the use of conventional or biologic DMTs. The second study reported on 806 Danish patients with inflammatory arthritis (RA, ankylosing spondylitis, psoriatic arthritis, or other) who also had a history of cervical neoplasia.<sup><xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref></sup> None of the patients experienced progression to CC, including those on DMTs. The authors believed that their data were limited by short follow-up and small numbers, concluding that larger numbers of patients and longer follow-up are required to assess the risk associated with DMTs.</p><p>Several publications reported on the CC risk associated with unspecified DMTs or classes of DMTs. A national Swedish registry-based cohort study of patients with SLE treated with either immunosuppressive DMTs or antimalarials found an increase in cervical neoplasia and CC in the cohort receiving immunosuppressants (HR = 1.83; 95% CI = 1.15&#8211;2.91), but no increase in CIN 2+ (HR = 1.44; 95% CI = 0.82&#8211;2.54).<sup><xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref></sup> All 5 cases of invasive CC occurred in the immunosuppressants cohort, thus statistical evaluation was not performed. Among 341,758 Danish patients with various autoimmune disorders reported that the use of antimetabolites, systemic corticosteroids, or immunosuppressants, other than azathioprine, were not associated with the risk of CC.<sup><xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref></sup> Treatment with a cumulative high dose of azathioprine (&gt;300 mg defined daily doses) was associated with a hazard ratio of 2.2 (95% CI = 1.2&#8211;3.9). Of note, this analysis included patients during the period of 1995&#8211;2010, which likely did not include many of the drugs currently used to treat patients with autoimmune disorders. A cohort study of greater than 400,000 patients with RA treated with either biologic or nonbiologic DMTs identified 22,267 matched pairs.<sup><xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref></sup> Ninety-two percent of patients treated with a biologic DMT received a TNF inhibitor, most commonly etanercept. The most common nonbiologic DMT was methotrexate. Mean duration of treatment ranged from 1 to 2 years. The authors concluded that treatment with a biologic DMT was associated with a &#8220;numerically significant, but not statistically significant, increase in the risk of high-grade cervical neoplasia or CC&#8221; compared to treatment with a nonbiologic DMT. Short duration of treatment, however, limits the ability to draw conclusions from this study.</p><p>Another study identified 238 subjects with a history of previously treated HSIL among 11,738 patients with RA treated with either a nonbiologic DMT (48/2654) or a TNF inhibitor (190/9084).<sup><xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref></sup> Only 2 incident female genital cancers were reported during follow-up: 1 case each of metastatic squamous cell carcinoma of the vulva and metastatic CC, both in the nonbiologic DMT cohort. In each case, cervical SIL had occurred 13 years prior to the development of the incident cancer. The authors stated that a limitation of the study was the lack of power to detect a clinically important difference in cancer risk between cohorts. A Swedish nationwide register-based cohort study by Wadstr&#246;m et al. included 9,629 patients with RA beginning TNF inhibitor, 34,984 biologics-na&#239;ve patients with RA, and 300,331 general-population controls.<sup><xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref></sup> Patients were followed for up to 13 years. Compared to the biologics-na&#239;ve cohort, the TNF inhibitor cohort had a higher rate of CIN 2+ (HR = 1.36; 95% CI = 1.01&#8211;1.82) and a doubled risk of invasive CC (HR = 2.10; 95% CI = 1.04&#8211;4.32).</p><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Summary of Risk of HPV, SIL, CIN, and CC Screening in Patients on DMTs</title><p>Data regarding CC risk associated with individual DMTs are limited and often contradictory. Limitations of the available data include short time of follow-up, limited number of patients, and the confounding caused by switching from one medication to another during study periods. In addition, most of the women were followed very closely, hence early diagnosis and treatment of precancers may have masked the increased risk in CC. In many instances, recommendations are based on extrapolation from the risk associated with other viral infections such as herpes and hepatitis. Given the uncertainty of the risk associated with exposure to any individual DMT, we conclude that the evidence is insufficient to make a recommendation so shared decision-making is needed to individualize screening.</p></sec><sec><title>DMTs, MAB, and HPV Vaccine Immunogencity</title><p>Healthy plasma cells are an integral component of humoral immunity and the production of serum antibodies following vaccination. No data are available for the impact of DMTs or MAB on HPV vaccination specifically. In a limited study<sup><xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref></sup> of 30 patients with relapsed refractory multiple myeloma, there were no differences in antigen-specific antibody responses to <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> type B vaccinations between those who were daratumumab-na&#239;ve (55.6% and 62.5%, respectively) versus daratumumab-treated (68.8% and 66.7%, respectively; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .509 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = .842). In contrast, another study showed higher rates of nonresponse to pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine (OR = 9.51 [95% CI = 2.68&#8211;33.80]. Another group administered vaccines to 102 patients with relapsing MS randomized to receive either ocrelizumab, interferon B, or no DMT.<sup><xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref></sup> Exposure to ocrelizumab attenuated the response to tetanus toxoid-containing vaccine and 23-valent pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine.</p><p>In a study evaluating humoral response to COVID-19 vaccination in 912 Sardinian MS patients on various DMTs, those treated with natalizumab, teriflunomide, azathioprine, fingolimod, ocrelizumab, and rituximab showed significantly lower response compared to untreated controls.<sup><xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref></sup> No differences in response were seen for those treated with dimethyl fumarate, interferon, alemtuzumab, or glatiramer acetate. In a separate study evaluating humor response 1 month after the second dose of COVID-19 vaccine in 140 patients on a variety of DMTs, all patients treated with first-line DMTs (natalizumab, cladribine, alemtuzumab) developed a measurable humoral response.<sup><xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref></sup> Among patients treated with ocrelizumab and fingolimod, the immune response was significantly lower and some failed to develop a measurable response. Time from last DMT infusion to vaccination was positively correlated with immune response. There were no significant side effects to vaccination regardless of DMT exposure.</p></sec><sec><title>Summary of HPV Vaccine Immunogenity and DMTs/MAB.</title><p>The impact of these therapies on patients previously vaccinated against HPV is unknown. In Australia, a 3-dose regimen of an HPV vaccine is recommended for immunocompromised patients of any age, including those on immunotherapies.<sup><xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref></sup> A 3-dose series of the HPV vaccine is recommended for all patients on DMTs at the recommended ages. If this can be performed prior to starting a DMT, this would be ideal.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>There are many limitations as pointed out in each section. The limitations include publications with small sample sizes, lack of inclusion of type of immunosuppressive therapies, short follow-up periods, and lack of histologic endpoints.</p><p>Summary of recommendations for each group reviewed is listed in Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. These summaries took into account the increased risk of cervical precancers and cancers for women living with SOT, HSCT, and SLE, hence the recommendations for enhanced screening frequency. It was also felt that there was both a theoretical risk as well as some evidence in the literature for any immunosuppressant use including DMT/MABs increasing risk for patients with RA, IBD, and MS, hence the recommendation for enhanced screening frequency in this group as well. The literature on RA, IBD, and MS not on immunosuppressants was very limited because the use of immunosuppressants were not always available. However, overall there did not appear to be an increased risk; therefore, we recommended following the guidelines for general populations with the caveat that shared decision-making for those with RA, IBD, and MS not on immunosuppressants is also appropriate. This was also true for all patients on any DMT or MABS since the literature for all other disease was scant. Given the theoretical risks and conflicting data, any women on DMT or MABS should have shared decision-making regarding screening frequency. We also emphasize that the CDC HIV CC guidelines include enhanced screening through the woman's lifetime as defined in Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Human papillomavirus vaccination at the CDC target age should not change the recommendations for increased CC screening surveillance. Data identify an increased risk of vulvar cancer in SOT and ESRD, and this risk may extend to other immunocompromised groups<sup><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> covered by this guideline, though studies are lacking. Potential for vulvar cancer should be considered during gynecologic care.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Summary of Cervical Cancer Screening and Vaccination Recommendations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="top"><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General-population cervical cancer screening</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased screening<italic toggle="yes"><sup>a</sup></italic> with immunosuppressant use</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased screening<italic toggle="yes"><sup>a</sup></italic> regardless of immunosuppressant use</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPV vaccination<italic toggle="yes"><sup>b</sup></italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solid organ transplant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">End-stage renal disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematopoietic stem cell transplant<italic toggle="yes"><sup>c</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systemic lupus erythematosus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rheumatoid arthritis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X<italic toggle="yes"><sup>d</sup></italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflammatory bowel disease</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X<italic toggle="yes"><sup>d</sup></italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple sclerosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X<italic toggle="yes"><sup>d</sup></italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease-modifying therapies or monoclonal antibodies</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X<italic toggle="yes"><sup>e</sup></italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X<italic toggle="yes"><sup>e</sup></italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>a</sup></italic>Increased screening recommendations are noted on Table <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>b</sup></italic>Human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccination ages per ACIP recommendations, starting at age 9 and extending up to age 26, with an option to vaccinate up to age 45 with shared decision-making. Recommend a 3-vaccine course in immunosuppressed adolescents rather than a 2-vaccine series. For solid organ transplant (SOT) candidates, administer HPV vaccination before the transplant when possible. See SOT section for further recommendations regarding vaccination around time of SOT. If HPV vaccination was given before hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT), the vaccine series should be restarted and can be administered up to age 45, following ACIP guidelines.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>c</sup></italic>Exceptions for HSCT recipients: if graft versus host disease develops, test cervical cytology annually until 3 consecutive normal results at which time perform cytology every 3 years. Alternatively, if aged 30 years or more, perform cotest at diagnosis and if cytology is normal and HPV is negative, perform cotesting every 3 years.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>d</sup></italic>Due to lack of data, shared decision-making about increased screening is reasonable for women with inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), rheumatoid arthritis (RA), and multiple sclerosis not on chronic immunosuppressant medication.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>e</sup></italic>Shared decision-making about increased screening should also be implemented for any women on DMT/MAB.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Recommendations<sup><xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> for Cervical Cancer Screening for Patients With HIV in the United States</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients living with HIV aged &lt;30 y</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; Screening is recommended to start at the age 21 y</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; Patients living with HIV aged 21&#8211;29 y should have a cytology test after initial diagnosis.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; Cytology test should be performed at baseline and every 12 mo (BII).</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If results of 3 consecutive cytology tests are normal, follow-up cytology tests can be performed every 3 y (BII)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; Cotesting (cytology test and HPV test) is not recommended for patients younger than 30 y.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If ASCUS/HPV+ or LSIL or worse is found, referral to colposcopy is recommended (AII)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If HPV-negative ASCUS or ASCUS with no HPV test, repeat cytology test in 6&#8211;12 mo. (AII)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; Refer to colposcopy if repeat abnormal (AII)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patients living with HIV aged &#8805;30 y cytology testing only</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; After initial HIV diagnosis, cytology test should be performed at baseline and every 12 mo (BII).</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If results of 3 consecutive cytology tests are normal, follow-up cytology tests can be performed every 3 y (BII).</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; Follow-up of abnormal test as for &lt;30 y</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Or</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytology test and HPV cotesting:</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; After initial HIV diagnosis, cytology test and HPV cotesting should be performed at baseline (BII).</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If result of the cytology test is normal and HPV cotesting is negative, follow-up cytology test and HPV cotesting can be performed every 3 y (BII).</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If the result of the cytology test is normal but HPV cotesting is positive:</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Either</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; Follow-up test with cytology test and HPV cotesting should be performed in 1 y.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If the 1-y follow-up cytology test is abnormal or HPV cotesting is positive, referral to colposcopy is recommended.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Or</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; Perform HPV genotyping.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If positive for HPV 16 or HPV 18, colposcopy is recommended.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If negative for HPV 16 and HPV 18, repeat cotest in 1 y is recommended. If the follow-up HPV test is positive or cytology test is abnormal, colposcopy is recommended.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Or</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytology test and HPV 16 or HPV 16/18 specified in cotesting:</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; Perform HPV genotyping.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If positive for HPV 16 or HPV 18, colposcopy is recommended.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If negative for HPV 16 and HPV 18, repeat cotest in 1 y is recommended. If the follow-up HPV test is positive or cytology test is abnormal, colposcopy is recommended.</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Or</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytology test and HPV 16 or HPV 16/18 specified in cotesting:</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; After initial HIV diagnosis, cytology test and HPV 16 or 16/18 cotesting should be performed at baseline (BII).</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8226; If result of the cytology test is normal and HPV 16 or 16/18 cotesting is negative,</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">follow-up cytology test and HPV cotesting can be performed every 3 y (BII).</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*If initial test or followup test is positive for HPV 16 or 16/18, referral to colposcopy is recommended (BII).</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="other"><p>Screening is currently recommended through a patient's lifetime with discontinuation based on shared decision-making and quality of life.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>ASCUS indicates atypical squamous cells of undetermined significance; LSIL, low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesion.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Nuances for Those Living With an HSCT</title><p>It is recommended that if an individual is being screened with cytology only and develops genital GVHD, the screening return to annual cytology for 3 consecutive screenings and, if normal, thereafter every 3 years for cytology screening. If being screened with cotesting, and no test was performed in the last year, a repeat with cotesting should be performed.</p><sec><title>HPV Vaccine Recommendations</title><p>A 3-dose series of the HPV vaccine is recommended for all age-eligible patients described above. As with the general population, vaccination at early ages is more likely to prevent HPV-related morbidity and mortality. Routinely vaccinating young patients, starting at 9 years of age, is recommended with catch-up to 26 years of age. Vaccination from age 27 up to age 45 years as approved in the ACIP guidelines should be considered in shared decision-making.</p><p>For SOT, when possible, HPV vaccine series should be initiated and completed before the SOT. If complete vaccination is not possible pretransplant, 1 dose should ideally be administered pretransplant, and the series should be resumed 6 months after SOT. Risk of acquiring HPV versus deferring HPV vaccination should be taken into account.</p><p>For HSCT, if the HSCT occurred after the HPV vaccine was administered, the vaccine series should be readministered up to age 45 years as approved in the ACIP guidelines.</p><p>For DMT/MCA, the HPV vaccine series should be initiated before starting treatment when possible.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Clinical and Public Health Implications</title><p>Key clinical implications include the need for more frequent screenings at an earlier onset, enhanced HPV vaccination monitoring, and interdisciplinary collaboration among health care providers. Public health considerations involve allocating resources for timely screenings, tracking vaccination outcomes, addressing health disparities through customized screening initiatives for varied communities, and ensuring access to specialized care to facilitate management of abnormal cells. Overall, improving CC outcomes in this specific population requires a comprehensive approach that combines clinical care among gynecologists, primary care providers, oncologists, pediatricians, and immunologists with culturally proactive public health strategies.</p></sec><sec><title>Future Directions</title><p>As immunosuppressants become less toxic and more personalized, it will be critical to continue to examine the literature. Large databases or registries that are able to collect data on specific immunosuppressant agents and HPV vaccination histories are most likely to contribute to solid evidence for CC risk.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>The authors have declared they have no conflicts of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moscicki</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huchko</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Guidelines for cervical cancer screening in immunosuppressed women without HIV infection</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Low Genit Tract Dis</italic></source><year>2019</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30907775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/LGT.0000000000000468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group><collab collab-type="authors">National Institutes of Health CfDCaP, HIV Medicine Association, and Infectious Diseases Society of America</collab></person-group>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Guidelines for the Prevention and Treatment of Opportunistic Infections in Adults and Adolescents With HIV</italic></source>. <year>2024</year>:<fpage>Q4&#8211;6, Q15</fpage><comment>Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://clinicalinfo.hiv.gov/sites/default/files/guidelines/documents/adult-adolescent-oi/guidelines-adult-adolescent-oi.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://clinicalinfo.hiv.gov/sites/default/files/guidelines/documents/adult-adolescent-oi/guidelines-adult-adolescent-oi.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed July 3, 2024</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guido</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>2019 ASCCP Risk-Based Management Consensus Guidelines for Abnormal Cervical Cancer Screening Tests and Cancer Precursors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Low Genit Tract Dis</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>102</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32243307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/LGT.0000000000000525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7147428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guido</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>2019 ASCCP Risk-Based Management Consensus Guidelines: Updates Through 2023</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Low Genit Tract Dis</italic></source><year>2024</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38117563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/LGT.0000000000000788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10755815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontham</surname><given-names>ETH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>AMD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cervical cancer screening for individuals at average risk: 2020 guideline update from the American Cancer Society</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">CA Cancer J Clin</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32729638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <collab collab-type="authors">To CH</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Immunogenicity and safety of a quadrivalent human papillomavirus vaccine in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus: a case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Rheum Dis</italic></source><year>2013</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22589375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/annrheumdis-2012-201393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panicker</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunogenicity of quadrivalent human papillomavirus vaccine in organ transplant recipients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Transplant</italic></source><year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>2411</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23837399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ajt.12329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4583130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Parra-Avila</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez-Santana</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr&#243;n-S&#225;nchez</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence of cervical intraepithelial lesions and human papilloma virus infection in female renal transplant recipients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transpl Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>e13622</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33877726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/tid.13622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyaji</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Infante</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picone</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human papillomavirus (HPV) seroprevalence, cervical HPV prevalence, genotype distribution and cytological lesions in solid organ transplant recipients and immunocompetent women in Sao Paulo, Brazil</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PloS One</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e0262724</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35051227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0262724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8775251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinholdt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dehlendorff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human papillomavirus-related anogenital premalignancies and cancer in renal transplant recipients: a Danish nationwide, registry-based cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Cancer</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>146</volume>:<fpage>2413</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31291470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.32565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Thimm</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rositch</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VandenBussche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lower genital tract dysplasia in female solid organ transplant recipients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obstet Gynecol</italic></source><year>2019</year>;<volume>134</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31306332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000003378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7453406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin-Hong</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <collab collab-type="authors">AST Infectious Diseases Community of Practice</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Human papillomavirus infection in solid organ transplant recipients: guidelines from the American Society of Transplantation Infectious Diseases Community of Practice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Transplant</italic></source><year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>e13590</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31077438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ctr.13590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bangdiwala</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vock</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Post-transplant malignancy after pediatric kidney transplantation: retrospective analysis of incidence and risk factors in 884 patients receiving transplants between 1963 and 2015 at the University of Minnesota</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Coll Surg</italic></source><year>2017</year>;<volume>225</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28445794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2017.04.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>AMHN</surname><given-names>Noone</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krapcho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brest</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruhl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatalovich</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feuer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group> (eds). <source><italic toggle="yes">SEER Cancer Statistics Review, 1975&#8211;2015</italic></source>. <comment>Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://seer.cancer.gov/csr/1975_2015/" ext-link-type="uri">https://seer.cancer.gov/csr/1975_2015/</ext-link>. Accessed April 2018</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baecklund</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pediatric organ transplantation and risk of premalignant and malignant tumors in Sweden</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Transplant</italic></source><year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21199354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1600-6143.2010.03367.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaung</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martella</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for abnormal cervical cytology in women undergoing kidney transplant evaluation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Clin Transplant</italic></source><year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.6002/ect.2017.0064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29251578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and risk factors for HPV-associated cancers in women with end-stage renal disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Invest Med</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>1002</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jim-2019-001262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32503931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Causal association between chronic kidney disease and risk of 19 site-specific cancers: a Mendelian randomization study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1233</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35333923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-21-1318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Skov Dalgaard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fassel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#216;stergaard</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of human papillomavirus-related cancers among kidney transplant recipients and patients receiving chronic dialysis&#8212;an observational cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Nephrol</italic></source><year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23834996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2369-14-137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3710213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Boey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curinckx</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roelants</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunogenicity and safety of the 9-valent human papillomavirus vaccine in solid organ transplant recipients and adults infected with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Infect Dis</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>e661</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33373429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/cid/ciaa1897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdulnoor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunogenicity of a quadrivalent human papillomavirus vaccine in pediatric kidney and liver transplant recipients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Transplant</italic></source><year>2023</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>e14476</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36740761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/petr.14476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunogenicity of human papillomavirus recombinant vaccine in children with CKD</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</italic></source><year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>776</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27055465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2215/CJN.09690915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4858485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverberg</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leyden</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of 'catch-up' human papillomavirus vaccination to prevent cervical neoplasia in immunosuppressed and non-immunosuppressed women</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vaccine</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>4520</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32446836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vaccine.2020.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7272293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Danziger-Isakov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <collab collab-type="authors">AST ID Community of Practice</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Vaccination of solid organ transplant candidates and recipients: guidelines from the American Society of Transplantation Infectious Diseases Community of Practice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Transplant</italic></source><year>2019</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>e13563</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31002409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ctr.13563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chelmow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cejtin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conageski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Executive summary of the Lower Anogenital Tract Cancer Evidence Review conference</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Obstet Gynecol</italic></source><year>2023</year>;<volume>142</volume>:<fpage>708</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37543740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/AOG.0000000000005283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10424818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased incidence of human papillomavirus-related precancer or second malignancy among allogeneic stem cell transplantation patients: A SEER-Medicare population study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Transplant Cell Ther</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1016.e1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jtct.2021.08.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8671185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34474166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of secondary nonhematologic malignancies after allogeneic stem cell transplantation: a nationwide case-control cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Cancer</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>151</volume>:<fpage>1024</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35554932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.34115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Stratton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Battiwalla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immune response following quadrivalent human papillomavirus vaccination in women after hematopoietic allogeneic stem cell transplant: a nonrandomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA Oncol</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>696</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>705</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32105293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jamaoncol.2019.6722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7144415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>QF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High-risk human papilloma virus infection and cervical neoplasm in female inflammatory bowel disease patients: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gastroenterol Rep (Oxf)</italic></source><year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31687153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/gastro/goy053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6821219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malloy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jokubaitis</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased risk of cervical dysplasia in females with autoimmune conditions&#8212;results from an Australia database linkage study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PloS One</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e0234813</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32555638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0234813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7302686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruis</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sch&#246;mig-Markiefka</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of abnormal Pap smear results in inflammatory bowel disease: a prospective study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>3071</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34981194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00432-021-03909-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11800968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Segal</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Askari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The incidence and prevalence of human papilloma virus-associated cancers in IBD</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Inflamm Bowel Dis</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32080713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ibd/izaa035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Elevated risk of cervical cancer in elderly women with incident ulcerative colitis in South Korea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source><year>2023</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>8323</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37221276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-023-33476-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10205754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Goetgebuer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreijne</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased risk of high-grade cervical neoplasia in women with inflammatory bowel disease: a case-controlled cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Crohns Colitis</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1464</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33609353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ecco-jcc/jjab036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8653760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreijne</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goetgebuer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erler</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cumulative exposure to immunomodulators increases risk of cervical neoplasia in women with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aliment Pharmacol Ther</italic></source><year>2023</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37221820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/apt.17555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between inflammatory bowel disease and risk of abnormalities of uterine cervix</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Obstet Gynaecol Res</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>4030</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34528331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jog.14992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jess</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of cervical cancer in inflammatory bowel disease: a meta-analysis of population-based studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Transl Gastroenterol</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e00513</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35905421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14309/ctg.0000000000000513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10476713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bousvaros</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunogenicity and tolerability to human papillomavirus-like particle vaccine in girls and young women with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Inflamm Bowel Dis</italic></source><year>2013</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1441</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23567780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MIB.0b013e318281341b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3677764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#237;a-Carrasco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendoza-Pinto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas-Villarraga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of cervical HPV infection in women with systemic lupus erythematosus: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Autoimmun Rev</italic></source><year>2019</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>184</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30572140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.autrev.2018.09.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The five major autoimmune diseases increase the risk of cancer: epidemiological data from a large-scale cohort study in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cancer Commun (Lond)</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35357093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cac2.12283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9118055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Systemic lupus erythematosus is a risk factor for cancer: a nationwide population-based study in Korea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lupus</italic></source><year>2019</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30712493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0961203319826672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between systemic lupus erythematosus and cancer morbidity and mortality: findings from cohort studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Oncol</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>860794</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35600353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fonc.2022.860794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9115099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The risks of cancer development in systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arthritis Res Ther</italic></source><year>2018</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>270</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30522515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13075-018-1760-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6282326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pooley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marjenberg</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of malignancy in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Semin Arthritis Rheum</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>1230</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34710720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.semarthrit.2021.09.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Soybilgic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onel</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Utset</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Safety and immunogenicity of the quadrivalent HPV vaccine in female systemic lupus erythematosus patients aged 12 to 26 years</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pediatr Rheumatol Online J</italic></source><year>2013</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23924237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1546-0096-11-29</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3751269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhar</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Essenmacher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The safety and immunogenicity of quadrivalent HPV (qHPV) vaccine in systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vaccine</italic></source><year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>2642</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28404357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vaccine.2017.04.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotstein Grein</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Safety and immunogenicity of the quadrivalent human papillomavirus vaccine in patients with childhood systemic lupus erythematosus: a real-world interventional multi-centre study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lupus</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>934</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32501172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0961203320928406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <collab collab-type="authors">To CH</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Long-term immunogenicity of a quadrivalent human papillomavirus vaccine in systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vaccine</italic></source><year>2018</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>3301</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29699792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vaccine.2018.04.056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Infante</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyaji</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soarez</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review and meta-analysis of HPV vaccination in women with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Vaccines</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33573404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/14760584.2021.1889375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chadwick</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearsley-Fleet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cervical screening uptake and rates of cervical dysplasia in the British Society for Rheumatology Biologics Register for Rheumatoid Arthritis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rheumatology (Oxford)</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>59</volume>:<fpage>559</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31722431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/rheumatology/kez277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heijstek</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scherpenisse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunogenicity and safety of the bivalent HPV vaccine in female patients with juvenile idiopathic arthritis: a prospective controlled observational cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Rheum Dis</italic></source><year>2014</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>1500</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23723319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/annrheumdis-2013-203429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Esposito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corona</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barzon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunogenicity, safety and tolerability of a bivalent human papillomavirus vaccine in adolescents with juvenile idiopathic arthritis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Expert Rev Vaccines</italic></source><year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1387</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25066387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1586/14760584.2014.943195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Contribution of viral infection to risk for cancer in systemic lupus erythematosus and multiple sclerosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PloS One</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e0243150</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33481783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0243150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7822541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Alping</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Askling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer risk for fingolimod, natalizumab, and rituximab in multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Neurol</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>688</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32056253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ana.25701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rostgaard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer risk among patients with multiple sclerosis: a population-based register study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Cancer</italic></source><year>2006</year>;<volume>118</volume>:<fpage>979</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16152598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.21437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dugu&#233;</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebolj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of cervical cancer in women with autoimmune diseases, in relation with their use of immunosuppressants and screening: population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Cancer</italic></source><year>2015</year>;<volume>136</volume>:<fpage>E711</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25220731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ijc.29209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahmanyar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer risk among patients with multiple sclerosis and their parents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source><year>2009</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>1170</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19332695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/01.wnl.0000345366.10455.62</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemminki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of autoimmune diseases on risk and survival in female cancers</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Gynecol Oncol</italic></source><year>2012</year>;<volume>127</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22819787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ygyno.2012.07.100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fois</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wotton</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeates</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer in patients with motor neuron disease, multiple sclerosis and Parkinson's disease: record linkage studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</italic></source><year>2010</year>;<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19726405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/jnnp.2009.175463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingwell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bajdik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer risk in multiple sclerosis: findings from British Columbia, Canada</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brain</italic></source><year>2012</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>2973</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22730559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/brain/aws148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Moisset</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peri&#233;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Decreased prevalence of cancer in patients with multiple sclerosis: a case-control study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PloS One</italic></source><year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0188120</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29176769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0188120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5703510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hongell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumelahti</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Risk of cancer among Finnish multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mult Scler Relat Disord</italic></source><year>2019</year>;<volume>35</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31404761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.msard.2019.08.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grytten</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myhr</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Celius</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence of cancer in multiple sclerosis before and after the treatment era&#8212;a registry-based cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mult Scler Relat Disord</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>103209</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34419754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.msard.2021.103209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrie</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer incidence and mortality rates in multiple sclerosis: a matched cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>e501</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33239364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/WNL.0000000000011219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mailand</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frederiksen</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vaccines and multiple sclerosis: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Neurol</italic></source><year>2017</year>;<volume>264</volume>:<fpage>1035</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27604618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00415-016-8263-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>SCW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Conventional and biologic disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs are not associated with increase in or progression of cervical neoplasia among patients with spondyloarthritis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Rheumatol</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>e63</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33105316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/RHU.0000000000001590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordtz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mellemkj&#230;r</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glintborg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Malignant progression of precancerous lesions of the uterine cervix following biological DMARD therapy in patients with arthritis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Rheum Dis</italic></source><year>2015</year>;<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>1479</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25744102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/annrheumdis-2014-206909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wadstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arkema</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sj&#246;wall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cervical neoplasia in systemic lupus erythematosus: a nationwide study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rheumatology (Oxford)</italic></source><year>2017</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>613</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28039412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/rheumatology/kew459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5850736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneeweiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Biologic disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs and risk of high-grade cervical dysplasia and cervical cancer in rheumatoid arthritis: a cohort study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Arthritis Rheumatol</italic></source><year>2016</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>2106</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27015113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/art.39689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5001884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Low</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-TNF therapy in women with rheumatoid arthritis with a history of carcinoma in situ of the cervix</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Rheum Dis</italic></source><year>2013</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22843488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/annrheumdis-2012-201814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Wadstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frisell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spar&#233;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Do RA or TNF inhibitors increase the risk of cervical neoplasia or of recurrence of previous neoplasia? A nationwide study from Sweden</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ann Rheum Dis</italic></source><year>2016</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>1272</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26755797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/annrheumdis-2015-208263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Frerichs</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosman</surname><given-names>PWC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Velzen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of daratumumab on normal plasma cells, polyclonal immunoglobulin levels, and vaccination responses in extensively pre-treated multiple myeloma patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Haematologica</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>e302</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31558675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3324/haematol.2019.231860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7271608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bar-Or</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calkwood</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chognot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of ocrelizumab on vaccine responses in patients with multiple sclerosis: the VELOCE study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurology</italic></source><year>2020</year>;<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>e1999</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2008</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32727835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1212/WNL.0000000000010380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7843152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pitzalis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Idda</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodde</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of different disease-modifying therapies on humoral response to BNT162b2 vaccine in Sardinian multiple sclerosis patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Immunol</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>781843</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34956211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2021.781843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8697018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Capone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucchini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunogenicity and safety of mRNA COVID-19 vaccines in people with multiple sclerosis treated with different disease-modifying therapies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neurotherapeutics</italic></source><year>2022</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34859382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13311-021-01165-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8639214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nesbitt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rath</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Vaccinations in patients with multiple sclerosis: review and recommendations</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med J Aust</italic></source><year>2021</year>;<volume>214</volume>:<fpage>350</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>354.e1</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33866556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5694/mja2.51012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>