<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2277</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">frontpubhealth</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2565</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9614426</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9614426.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9614426</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9614426</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36311597</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.912946</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A scoping review on population-centered indicators for cancer care continuum</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajaguru</surname><given-names initials="V">Vasuki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1263898/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names initials="J">Jieun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1654283/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names initials="JA">Jeoung A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2013667/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="JH">Jae Hyun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1487335/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names initials="J">Jaeyong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chun</surname><given-names initials="M">Mison</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1438614/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Healthcare Management, Graduate School of Public Health, Yonsei University</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Hinda and Arthur Marcus Institute for Aging Research, Hebrew SeniorLife, Harvard Medical School, Boston</institution>, <addr-line>Massachusetts</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Institute of Health Services Research, Yonsei University</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Health Administration, Dankook University</institution>, <addr-line>Cheonan</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Preventive Medicine, College of Medicine, Yonsei University</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, School of Medicine, Ajou University</institution>, <addr-line>Suwon</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Surapaneni Krishna Mohan, Panimalar Medical College Hospital and Research Institute, India</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Jeoungmi Kim, Kaya University, South Korea; Bijaya Kumar Padhi, Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research (PGIMER), India</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Jaeyong Shin <email>drshin@yuhs.ac</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Mison Chun <email>chunm@ajou.ac.kr</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Public Health Education and Promotion, a section of the journal Frontiers in Public Health</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400439</issue-id><elocation-id>912946</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>4</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-28 20:26:21.187"><day>28</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Rajaguru, Jang, Kwon, Kim, Shin and Chun.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Rajaguru, Jang, Kwon, Kim, Shin and Chun</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fpubh-10-912946.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>The purpose of this study was to develop prioritized cancer indicators and measure the population-based monitoring of the entire life cycle of cancer care, guiding the improvement of care delivery systems.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Scoping review was performed based on the Joanna Briggs Institute's methodology. Electronic databases were searched in PubMed, Cochrane Library, EMBASE, Ovid Medline, RISS, KISS, and KoreaMed. The searches were limited to articles published in English between 2010 and 2020. No restrictions were applied regarding the publication status or country of origin, and all study designs were included. Gray literature was used to broaden the search's scope, identify new recommendations, need to be in connect with subject experts, and explore pertinent websites. The process and selected indicators were analyzed based on their frequency distribution and percentage.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The literature search yielded 6,202 works. In addition, national and international cancer guidelines were obtained from official database reports. A total of 35 articles and 20 reports regarding cancer indicators were finally selected for data synthesis. Based on them, 254 core sets of cancer indicators were identified. The selected indicators were classified into six domains based on the continuum of cancer care and survivor's life cycle, namely, primary prevention (61, 24.0%), secondary prevention (46, 18.1%), treatment (85, 33.5%), quality of care (33, 13.0%), survivor management (33, 13.0%), and end-of-life care (14, 5.5%).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>There is a growing interest in developing specific areas of cancer care. Cancer indicators can help organizations, care providers, and patients strive for optimal care outcomes. The identified indicators could guide future innovations by identifying weaknesses in cancer prevention and management.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cancer</kwd><kwd>indicators</kwd><kwd>cancer care</kwd><kwd>monitoring</kwd><kwd>quality improvement</kwd><kwd>population</kwd><kwd>review</kwd><kwd>health care</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>National Cancer Center</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100008746</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="68"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="8525"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cancer is one of the leading causes of death in Korea, where 243,263 new cancer cases and 80,546 cancer deaths are expected in 2020 (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Although the cancer incidence rates are anticipated to decrease slightly, the burden of most types of cancer will continue to grow as the population ages (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>The Korea Central Cancer Registry is a nationwide, hospital-based cancer registry initiated by the Korean Ministry of Health and Welfare in 1980 (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). It compares the status of cancer care based on the 5-year relative survival rates. For instance, 5-year relative survival rate of Korea's cervical cancer is 76.8%, and that of colorectal cancer is 63.7%, the best among the member nations of the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD). The nation's breast cancer survival rate is 82.2% like the OECD average (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>There are a growing number of studies related to cancer indicators. However, they focus on very specific aspects, such as incidence and mortality, special procedures or radiological treatment, and palliative care. Population-based cancer registries (PBCRs) complementing incidence and mortality by types of cancer have been collected, and it included as one of the 25 core indicators among non-communicable disease Global Monitoring Framework; the necessary technical support in planning and developing PBCRs in low-, middle-, and high-income countries is being provided through the International Association for Research on Cancer (IARC)-led partnership, the Global Initiative for Cancer Registry Development, and has presented a framework for managing patients with cancer based on the cancer life cycle, dividing it into four groups, namely, healthy population, early diagnosis, living with cancer, and dying (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Therefore, this review focused on developing cancer indicators as per the framework.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Conceptual framework of population-based cancer indicators and measurement for entire life cycle of cancer care level. Adapted from Pi&#241;eros et al. (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). PBCR, Population-Based Cancer Registry; DALYs, Disability-Adjusted Life-Years.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-10-912946-g0001.jpg"/></fig><p>Several studies on the performance or quality indicators of cancer care have shown that the indicators are associated with an improvement in either patient satisfaction or care quality (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Furthermore, many reports have focused on the development of effective therapies, the implementation of clinical practice guidelines, healthcare provision through multidisciplinary and interprofessional teams at all stages of the disease, and patient-centered care (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). There are limited studies reported regarding the population-based monitoring of cancer indicators that encompass the specific types of the cancer-care continuum (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). However, minimal attention has been paid to the life cycle of the cancer or the cancer-care continuum. Many new approaches have also emerged. However, there is no study that focuses on the entire life cycle of cancer care. Therefore, the aim of this study was to develop a population-based monitoring of cancer indicators and measurement for the entire life cycle of cancer care.</p><p>Scoping reviews are widely used to draw a map and analyze the existing scientific evidence in complex or relatively unexamined fields. We, therefore, initially preferred to review and compare the perspectives and attributes of the national and international cancer care guidelines. The current scoping review sought to find, examine, and describe the scientific literature on cancer indicators related to the measurement of community-based monitoring for the span of cancer care. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first scoping review to examine population-based cancer monitoring for the entire life cycle of cancer.</p><p>The purpose of this study was to identify the existing scientific literature and international guidelines regarding cancer indicators for the population-based monitoring of the entire continuum of cancer care using a scoping review methodology as prior knowledge of our ongoing project. In addition, the set of review will be providing the key knowledge of population-based cancer indicator measures that support the planning and evaluation of cancer indicators across the cancer-care continuum by elaborating the unique part of our ongoing project. In addition, we will continue this study in order to demonstrate how to concise the selected indicators with proper measurement by the numerator and denominator rate in the future by a panel discussion.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><p>This scoping review followed the six steps of the Arksey and O'Malley (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) and was conducted in compliance with the Preferred Reporting Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-Analyses (PRISMA) statement for scoping reviews (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). In addition, gray literature was performed to identify the existing national and international cancer indicators and guidelines.</p><sec><title>Research questions</title><p>By using the scoping review methodology, the following specific research questions have to be addressed:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>&#8220;What are the national and international guidelines of cancer indicators guidelines, which focus community, based monitoring of cancer indicators? And What are the types of monitoring indicators in cancer management have been reported?&#8221;</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#8220;What/Which are the patient, interventions, and outcomes with measurement of cancer indicators are currently in use or could potentially be used for measuring quality of cancer care in the population-based primary and acute or chronic setting across the life cycle of cancer-care continuum?&#8221;</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>Identification of relevant studies</title><p>Electronic databases such as PubMed, Medline, PsycINFO, Cochrane Library, Ovid EMBASE, KISS, KoreaMed, and RISS were used to search and identify the relevant scientific literature from May 2020 to September 2020 using a predefined search strategy. The search focused on articles published between 2010 and 2020, and the search terms were cancer OR cancer patients OR survivors AND monitoring AND indicator AND early detection<sup>*</sup> OR intervention<sup>*</sup> OR treatment<sup>*</sup> OR drug OR quality of life OR survivor<sup>*</sup> OR end of life OR palliative care OR Review<sup>*</sup> OR systematic review/ OR meta-analysis/ OR Guideline. These were reviewed to identify evidence-based recommendations.</p><p>The next step examined the existing national and international guidelines regarding the entire life cycle of cancer care based on the website of the American Society of Clinical Oncology and the guidelines of the European Union, World Health Organization, IARC, OECD, National Health Service, Canada, Japan, and South Korea. Some non-English guidelines were translated by the research team. Furthermore, problems resulting from unclear translation or unclear formulation were resolved through team discussion.</p><p>The next process was initiated by combining both the literature review and additional indicator guidelines. Each concept was converted into an indicator by formulating a definition, numerator, and denominator. All converted topics were checked for loss of information that could result from the research team's translation.</p></sec><sec><title>Study selection</title><p>All search results were exported from the electronic databases in the Research Information Systems format and imported into EndNote. Titles and abstracts were screened for eligibility, and duplicates were removed. The screening process was repeated by three researchers to ensure reproducibility and verify the outcomes. Articles that were finally selected for a full-text review were uploaded into EndNote. The quality of the studies was assessed using the PRISMA checklist for cross-sectional studies. The research team (VR, JJ, JAK, and JHK) conducted the appraisal collaboratively. The reviewed articles were independently assessed by two reviewers (VR and JJ) for fit and relevance, and full-text versions were evaluated to determine inclusion and exclusion. Team reviewers (JS, JAK, JHK, and M.C) examined the reviewed articles to resolve any disagreements through several meetings. All the review-related discussions and regular meetings were conducted. All the team members were unable to attend the regular meeting in person due to the COVID-19 pandemic. As a result, a hybrid mode that included offline and online Zoom conversations was deployed to distinguish between literature search and data synthesis.</p><sec><title>Inclusion criteria</title><p>This study focused on original articles on cancer indicators or index measurement activities and did not filter items based on country of origin, publication year, or publication status. Studies using mixed methods, including the Delphi technique, were also included. Studies on cancer indicators, early detection, quality of care, treatment, and end-of-life surveillance were prioritized for review.</p></sec><sec><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p>Studies published in other than English were excluded. In addition, poster presentations, commentaries, review articles, letters to the editor, and editorials were excluded. Articles that were not related to the quality of care and/or cancer indicators were excluded.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Charting the data (data extraction)</title><p>Data were extracted in PRISMA-ScR Checklist (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>) and organized the selected articles. Data collected from the literature were reviewed independently by the three researchers. Whenever discrepancies were identified, the researchers discussed these discrepancies and resolved them through consensus. The results were summarized in an Excel spreadsheet.</p></sec><sec><title>Collating, summarizing, and reporting the results</title><p>The extracted data chart is collated from the reviewed articles and summarized according to the study characteristics, including the author(s), publication year, country, purpose, research design, setting, target population, and methods of data collection, with the number of indicators and their characteristics (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). The findings were presented as a narrative synthesis and reported based on the heterogeneous nature of the reviewed articles. The selected indicators were composed of five aspects, namely &#8220;Classification,&#8221; &#8220;Participants,&#8221; &#8220;Domains,&#8221; &#8220;Subdomains,&#8221; and &#8220;Measurement&#8221; (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The classification focused on the health behavior and lifestyle of the general population toward the time-series (cancer continuum) concept of the occurrence and natural history of cancer diseases. Participants are considered patients (patients with cancer, including survivors), providers (the physician or oncologist who is evaluating the cancer-related medical services and resources), and family members of the patient with cancer. Domains indicate the health-related behavior of the patient such as healthcare utilization, resources, and availability of facilities. Subdomains are derived from the characteristics of the indicators based on time series, history of disease, and target cancer types. Measurement denotes the monitoring or assessment of the indicators based on target cancer and treatment (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables S3</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Vertical integration and significance cancer indicators monitoring by region. Indicators are composed of five vertical systems: &#8220;Classification,&#8221; &#8220;Participants,&#8221; &#8220;Domains,&#8221; &#8220;Subdomains,&#8221; and &#8220;Measurement.&#8221;</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-10-912946-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Consultation</title><p>Consultations were held with experts on cancer indicators and monitoring (e.g., medical professionals, oncologists, academics, and researchers). A multidisciplinary expert's opinion included forty-two experts to select the cancer measures according to the priority. We divided the experts into three groups, namely, researchers, policymakers, and clinicians. Then, we randomly selected five researchers, three policymakers, and three clinicians. Of the five researchers, two were from the internal research group, and the remaining three were from the national cancer center and other colleges. Of the three policymakers, one was a director of a public or community health service center, another from the Ministry of Health and Welfare, and the other from the National Cancer Center. For clinicians, we selected one oncologist, one internal physician, and one radio-oncologist. All expert members were contacted <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> email; the purpose of the project was explained, and consent was obtained. They reviewed and suggested revisions to the thematic chart based on the cancer life cycle, such as prevention, early diagnosis, treatment, quality of care, survivor management, and end-of-life care, and pointed out gaps in the indicators and the connection to community assessment.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Literature search and characteristics of the articles</title><p>A total of 6,202 articles were retrieved from the database, and 21 articles were retrieved through a manual search. A total of 3,234 articles remained after the removal of duplicates, and 2,195 were selected for screening. The retrieved documents were screened for eligibility based on their titles and abstracts. Finally, 35 articles (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) were selected for the final data synthesis (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Flow diagram for the literature search and article selection process.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fpubh-10-912946-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p>The characteristics of these studies are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The number of most published articles included five studies in Korea (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) and the United States (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), three studies in the Netherlands (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) and multinationals (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), and two studies in Switzerland (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), Australia (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), Canada (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), and Europe (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Only one least published study was included from the American Society of Cancer Organization (ASCO) (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), China (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), France (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), Italy (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), Morocco (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), Norway (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), Saudi Arabia (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), the UK (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), and Spain (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), and according to the year of publication, 75% of the articles were published between 2017 and 2020, indicating that the selected articles were relatively new with different details (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). The number of studies on target cancers in selected articles included seven studies focused on all types of cancers (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), six studies on colorectal (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), five studies on breast (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), three studies on cervical (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), lung (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), and bladder (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), two studies on each ovarian (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) and prostate (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), and one study on each colon (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), testicular (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), mesorectal (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), and palliative care (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). Most of the studies conducted in acute cancer medical and surgical settings in hospitals (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Some of the studies have been initiated by healthcare organizations and national-based projects by institutions. All the details of the study characteristics are described in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Description of the selected review articles.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>References</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Country</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Methods</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Outcome</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Design</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Target cancer</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Setting</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Data collection</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leow et al.<break/> (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systematic review</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bladder</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urologic surgery and special procedure data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urologic Surgery/Center for Surgery and Public Health</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min JK et al. (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modified Delphi method Expert Panel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital and public health center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National cancer screening data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indicators update and Propose performance targets.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bianchi et al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Switzerland</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Literature review Delphi method</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitals</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ticino Cancer Registry</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Set of quality indicators for whole diagnostic-treatment</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nazemi et al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bladder</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Cancer<break/> Institute's SEER</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National cancer institute's surveillance, epidemiology data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall survival rate and<break/> Disease-specific survival rate</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carlos et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASCO</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palliative care</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital, Clinic &amp; Community center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Death records of palliative care center data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perceived improvements in pain management</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partanen et al. (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweden Norway</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Network analysis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cervical</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National health center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based screening data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increased coverage rates and quality assurance</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Altobelli et al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Randomized controlled trials</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRC screening based on stool testing</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guideline for resources available</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sancho-M et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prospective cohort study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colon</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitals</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population based colon surgery data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identify risk factors for anastomotic leakage after bowel resection</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khare et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modified Delphi method, Expert Panel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bladder</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canadian Urologic Oncology Group</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific article</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development of quality indicators</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jung et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Cancer center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea National Cancer Incidence Database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-standardized rate of cancer continuum</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ramirez et al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed method</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community and clinic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBPR data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality of life of both general and disease-specific treatment follow-up</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vlayen et al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systematic review<break/> Expert panel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testicular</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgian Health Care Knowledge Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgian Cancer Registry data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Update- Evidence-based clinical practice guidelines</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vos EL et al. (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherland</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Validation study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitals</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nationwide, population-based registry</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variation of Quality of indicators according to hospital size</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gac et al. (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective cohort study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovarian</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer care hospitals</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European commission quality indicators data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluate the quality of ovarian cancer patient management</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Keikes et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherland</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systemic review</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Academic Medical Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific article</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development, evaluation, and validation of quality indicators</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ElNaggar et al. (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intervention study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovarian</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comprehensive Cancer Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Institutional ovarian cancer database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assess Society of Gynecologic Oncology quality measure</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gooiker et al. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Netherland</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expert Panel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nationwide, web-based database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Validate the quality indicators</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charaka et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morocco</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public Health Center Hospital</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National screening test data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monitoring quality improvement and enhance performance indicators</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampurno et al. (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA, UK Australia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modified Delphi method<break/> Expert panel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guideline Development</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Online survey and face-to-face meeting</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propose and update the quality indicators guidelines</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Watanabe et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modified Delphi method</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cervical</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital-based cancer registry Insurance claims data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adherence of standards of care across Japan</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tsiamis et al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Literature Review<break/> Modified Delphi Method</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Radiology care center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prostate Cancer Outcomes Registry-Australia &amp; New Zealand</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Develop quality indicators and monitor radiotherapy care</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boland et al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohort study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Cancer Institute</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Cancer Data Base</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage-specific survival</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jackson et al. (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA, UK Ireland Newzeland Australia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modified Delphi method<break/> Expert panel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colorectal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital Cancer research center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCCN and CCQMS Guidelines</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Update long-term survival rate guideline</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schneider et al. (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Switzerland</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meso rectal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical records</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demonstrate the local reoccurrence rate and special treatment</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hartmann-Johnsen et al. (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norway</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitudinal study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitals and clinic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All medical entries and Curate data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimation of the quality indicators for all hospital, treating breast cancer</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baili et al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systemic review Expert panel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European cancer indicator project center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population-based cancer registry database</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate the rehabilitation indicators in individual country and comparable across Europe</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeo et al. (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Descriptive study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tertiary and general hospitals</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health Insurance Review and Assessment</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Implementation of newer indicators in lung cancer care</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lee et al. (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Literature review</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific article</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimation 3-years survival rate</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biganzoli et al. (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Literature Review<break/> Benchmarking</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitals<break/> Breast cancer centers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific article</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Set the international and national level to audit quality indicators</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anfinan and Sait (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saudi Arabia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cervical</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tertiary care center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical records</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8-years survival rate</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kim et al. (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Literature review Expert Panel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific article</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Update and implement the existing guidelines</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choi et al. (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLOBOCAN and OECD countries</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLOBOCAN 2012 database for all 34 OECD countries</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development of national cancer control policies in cancer screening</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rae et al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canada</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modified Delphi method Expert panel</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Research center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Existing indicators of adolescent and young adult [AYA] guidelines</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Update the system performance indicators</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wang et al. (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retrospective study</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitals</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical history record</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimations of survival rate</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Muller et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gray literature</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Research center</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific article and Data</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adherence to clinical quality indicator</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>USA, The United States of America; UK, United Kingdom; ASCO, American Society of Cancer Oncology; SEER, The Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results Program; WHO, World Health Organization; CBPR, Community, Based Participatory Research; NCCN, The National Comprehensive Cancer Network; CCQMS, Cancer Care Quality Measurement System; GLOBOCAN, Global Cancer Observatory; OECD, The Organization for Economic Co, operation and Development.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The national and international guidelines for cancer care search comprised 1,116 indicators (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>), and all the details included organizations such as WHO (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), IARC (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), OECD (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), ASCO (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), National Health Service (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), the UK, Center for Cancer Control and Information Services, National Cancer Center, Japan (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>), National Cancer Center (NCC), Korea (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>), and other government and non-government organizations (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). All the details such as name of the organization, year of publication, population coverage, and number of indicators are listed in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. All the reviewed articles and guidelines were converted into indicators that were linked to either prevention, early diagnosis, treatment, quality of care, survivor management, or end-of-life care.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the national and international cancer guidelines.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Level</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cancer guidelines and reports</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Organization</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Publication</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Population coverage</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>No.of indicators</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International<break/> Guidelines</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer control and world cancer report (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International Agency for Research on Cancer [IARC]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009&#8211;2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canadian cancer society (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CANADA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015&#8211;2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National, Regional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">European guide for quality national cancer control programs (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#8211;2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National cancer care plan (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Organization for Economic Co&#8211;operation and Development [OECD]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#8211;2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality oncology practice initiative (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">American Society of Clinical Oncology [ASCO]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#8211;2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scottish cancer task force national cancer quality steering group guidelines and indicators (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Health Service [NHS]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013&#8211;2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WHO&#8211;Cancer care Report for ALL (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">World Health Organization [WHO]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2005&#8211;2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National cancer registration hospitals such as cancer treatment&#8211;linked hospitals (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Center for Cancer Control and Information Services, National Cancer Center&#8211; Japan</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer hospital&#8211; five&#8211;year survival rate report 2010&#8211;2011 (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer care linked hospital&#8211; Survival rate report &#8211; 2013 (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer statistics 2019 (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National screening programme DATA book (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monitoring of cancer incidence in Japan (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer incidence rate in Japan (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer and Disease Control Division, Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare&#8211;Japan</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National<break/> Guidelines</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer statistics (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Cancer Center [NCC] Korea</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007&#8211;2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measures to improve the classification system and evaluation of health indicators (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health Insurance Review and Assessment Service Korea</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional health index (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea Health Ranking [Elio &amp; company]</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional health vulnerable indicators (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korea Health Promotion Institute</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community health Survey&#8211;Health indicators (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hallym University</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2013</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community health Survey (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Center for Disease Control Korea</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008&#8211;2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regional</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Characteristics of cancer indicators</title><p>A wide variety of 254 cancer indicators and measures are retrieved across the literature as a whole and listed in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S5</xref>. Consistent with its search strategies, the study found literature reviews and guidelines that combined population-based monitoring with the entire life cycle of cancer care. Over all findings of the cancer indicators according to the classification, most of them were treatment (33.5%), then primary prevention (24%), secondary prevention (18.1%), quality of life (13%), end-of-life care (6%), and less percentage found in survivor management (5.5%). In terms of participants, most of them were administrators (154/254), providers (73/254), and then patients (17/254) based on the classifications (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The subdomains are included specific procedures and treatments are widely used in cancer care settings (70/254), followed by hospital professionals (28/254) and incidence-related cancer indicators (18/254). All the frequency and percentage of participants and subdomains based on the main classifications are given in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref>, <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Distribution of cancer indicators according to the participants.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Classification/</bold><break/>
<bold>participants</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Primary prevention</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Secondary prevention</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Treatment</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Quality of care</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Survivor management</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>End of life care</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Provider</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Administrator</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Provider/administrator</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient/administrator</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient/family</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient/family/administrator</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient/administrator/provider</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total (%)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>61 (24.0)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>46 (18.1)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>85 (33.5)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>33 (13.0)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>14 (5.5)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15 (6.0)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>254 (100)</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of cancer indicators according to the sub domains.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Classification/</bold><break/>
<bold>subdomains</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Primary prevention</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Secondary prevention</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Treatment</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Quality of care</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Survivor management</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>End of life care</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nutrition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical activity</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Research &amp; investment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High risk for infection</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High risk for chronic disease</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High risk for occupation environment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health care system</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health professionals</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccine/immunization</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General health checkup</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Facilities</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient&#8211;centered</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment/consultation/ interruption rate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment plan &amp; record</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific procedure and treatment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health expenditure</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Survival/mortality</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>61[24.0]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>46[18.1]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>85[33.5]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>33[13.0]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15[5.9]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>14[5.5]</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>254[100]</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The aim of this study was to review the scientific articles and international guidelines for the development of cancer indicators and measurement for monitoring the life cycle of cancer care. We have appraised the use and reporting of scoping reviews from electronic databases to select cancer indicators, and our review retrieved 35 scientific articles and national and international cancer care guidelines by gray literature search. Most of the studies from Korea and the USA in equal and consists of population- and patient-level indicators between 2010 and 2020. There was remarkable variability in terms of cancer indicators among selected studies. Our findings were synthesized and reported by</p><p>classifications, participants, domains, subdomains, and measurements. It has been suggested that the population-based monitoring of the entire life cycle of cancer care would assess primary prevention, secondary prevention (early detection and diagnosis), treatment, quality of care, survivor management, and end-of-life care. All the classifications are interconnected with the domains and subdomains. Moreover, the study reports of all the guidelines and reviewed contents were converted into cancer indicators and further classified.</p><p>Cancer prevention can be achieved through primary, secondary, and tertiary methods. Primary prevention involves the practice of healthy behaviors to lower one's risk of developing cancer (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). This study found 61 indicators related to primary prevention that focused on the subdomains of obesity, physical activity, research and investment, alcohol, smoking, nutrition, high risk of infection, high risk of chronic disease, high risk of occupation and environment, medical care system, health professionals, and vaccination-immunizations. The Center for Disease Control recommends a healthy diet and at least 30 min of moderate physical activity on 5 or more days every week or at least 20 min of vigorous activity on 3 or more days every week (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Some studies have addressed the empowerment and education of people to facilitate healthy lifestyle choices related to tobacco use (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) and nutrition (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). The IARC reported a positive relationship between obesity and the incidence of several types of cancer, including postmenopausal breast cancer and cancers of the colon, endometrium, esophagus, and kidney. Some studies have also addressed the promotion and provision of vaccines that prevent cancer, such as the human papillomavirus (HPV) vaccine (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>).</p><p>A total of 46 indicators related to secondary prevention were identified, such as those concerning early detection and diagnosis (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>), incidence and prevalence rates (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>), healthcare system (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), and healthcare professionals (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Patient-oriented care and other cancer-related consultations were included in this second group of cancer indicators. Cancer screening in the general population refers to detecting cancer when no apparent symptoms are present. This is done with the aim of decreasing cancer-related morbidity and mortality (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). Indicators related to cancer screening were proposed and reinforced by several articles and guidelines (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Cancer screening has been reported to be effective, and screening tests must meet two criteria. First, the screening test should detect cancer prior to the development of symptoms. Second, the treatment should be initiated as soon as the presence of cancer is confirmed, which would result in improved outcomes (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>).</p><p>A total of 85 indicators related to treatment and appropriate special procedures were identified. Most treatment-related indicators are handled by health professionals who provide specialized care and monitoring (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Several studies have reported appropriate treatments or procedures, such as an endoscopy for stomach cancer (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), mammography for breast cancer (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), computed tomography (CT) and positron emission tomography (PET) for malignant cancer at each stage (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), sedated auditory brainstem response (SABR) for lung cancer (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), molecular test (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), colonoscopy for colorectal cancer (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), and colposcopy (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). In addition, international guidelines have discussed the treatment regimen of medications (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>), chemotherapy, radiotherapy, and neoadjuvant therapy (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Surgical indicators, such as granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>) and total or radical resection for stomach cancer and colorectal cancer (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), were also derived. However, indicators related to the treatment of cancer must focus on its early stages to avoid the metastatic or chronic suffering of patients with cancer. All the discussed indicators to be used near death might be based on patient's preferences. Therefore, treatment-related indicators and their measurement are necessary to reduce morbidity or mortality rates. However, the measurement of treatment indicators depends on the availability of the quality data obtained without any burden and gap in order to predict the actual results. Especially, chemotherapy use in the chronic stage might be challenging to measure in the settings, frequency of episodes may not be tracked, which may affect the outcomes. Therefore, some of the treatment indicators may disagree regarding whether it represents low or poor quality of care or improper documentation.</p><p>A total of 33 quality of care indicators were identified, which focused on the care of patients with cancer and their quality of life. Most of the indicators involved healthcare managers or administrators, followed by providers and patients and their families. The selected indicators were medical expenditure (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>) after surgical complications and follow-up care (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), possibility of the recurrence of cancer (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), medication follow-up (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), and mortality rate after surgery or potential cases (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Studies have focused on the quality-of-care indicators for each type of cancer (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). This scoping review demonstrated the most important indicators related to the quality of care. Therefore, before measuring the quality of care, we must identify, develop, analyze, and validate the reliability of indicators that can be measured and compared to assess the improvement of cancer care.</p><p>A total of 15 survivor management-related indicators were identified. The participants were healthcare managers or administrators who are involved in the improvement of the quality of post-treatment patient care. Most of the patient-focused indicators were centered on family, such as psychosocial support services (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), rehabilitation services (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), alternative diversional activities (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>), and follow-up care <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> hospital visits and health practice (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>), and assessment and management of psychosocial pain (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). However, there are many challenges in developing indicators for cancer survivor care from the national public health perspective. There is a need to develop structured training programs for survivor management alone to improve the quality of cancer care.</p><p>A total of 14 indicators related to end-of-life care were identified. Most of the participants were healthcare managers or administrators who are involved with the organizational structures, care facility centers, and patients. The subdomains retrieved were the prevalence of patients with cancer enrolled in the last year of palliative care (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>) or hospice care (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Health services and professionals are involved in quality improvement (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), recruitment of care providers and field workers (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>), financial support for childhood cancer care (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>), number of patients receiving hospice care per year (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), self-satisfaction survey of palliative care services (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), and evidence-based research and investment (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) related to end-of-life care. It was found that some contrast of practical barriers exists to implementing end-of-life cancer indicators, identifying that the relevant population is challenging to measure the settings or databases due to the difficulties in predicting the end-of-life period. In addition, the indicators are based on precise document restrictions such as communication, patient-reported outcomes, or preferences.</p><p>To measure public accountability at the regional level, this scoping review measured the collected indicators using regional-level healthcare data, national cancer center data, national cohort, and health insurance claims data, as well as cancer-specialized hospital data. Furthermore, most of the quality indicators were measured by the structure, process, and outcome method of Donabedian's model for quality of cancer care (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Therefore, selected cancer indicators will be designed to measure the entire life cycle of cancer care.</p><p>To discover the numerous gaps in the clinical care that is currently being delivered, additional implications of these findings will be applied among patients with cancer in community and clinical settings. We anticipate that our population-based measurements and preliminary cancer indicators will be useful directly or indirectly to other nations or areas looking to raise the standard of cancer care in accordance with their organizational structure.</p><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>There are some limitations in the existing studies and guidelines of cancer indicators from published scientific articles. First, it is possible that we did not find all the articles in this review, due to variance in keywords or search terms. Second, the presented conceptual framework for the entire life cycle of cancer care constructed by the research team, thus, would be needed to revise by the experts in future study. Third, there is unavailability of population-based indicators from individual studies; therefore, we could not be able to find the different methods of measurement of cancer indicators. Finally, we were not able to access the original data from the articles and international guidelines. Therefore, we would not be able to answer some questions including diagnostic procedures and treatment types. However, it is true that population-based monitoring of cancer indicators is a positive approach for measuring the entire life cycle of cancer care, and further extension of review would need to be conducted again in detail.</p></sec><sec><title>Future directions</title><p>Further validation and reduction of the indicators are needed to develop cancer indicators for the entire life cycle of cancer care relevant to prevention, early diagnosis, treatment, quality of care, survivor management, and end-of-life care. Extended measures also need to be broader. Therefore, the next step is to conduct a modified Delphi and expert panel discussion to develop national cancer indicators for the entire life cycle of cancer care. However, additional significant cancer indicators might be available that can be tailored to suit the health system's goals and improve the quality of cancer care in Korea.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The scoping review process provides guidance by selecting a subset of indicators that are widely accepted as relevant by those who will drive the improvement of the population-based monitoring of cancer indicators. As an additional advantage compared to the usual way of setting up national databases in South Korea, the present selected indicators will be revised by oncological professionals and the national cancer center committee. At present, there is a substantial interest in the development of cancer indicators in this field. The reviewed cancer indicators will be undergoing the Delphi process to further develop the current project. Thus, both the process and the resultant indicators may prove of interest to policymakers, clinicians, and researchers across South Korea.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="s11" ref-type="sec">Supplementary material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author/s.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>Ethical review and approval was not required for the study on human participants in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. Written informed consent for participation was not required for this study in accordance with the national legislation and the institutional requirements.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JS and MC conceptualized and supervised the project. JAK, JHK, VR, and JJ performed data curation and synthesis. VR and JS wrote the paper. All authors reviewed the manuscript. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>This scoping review was conducted as part of the Regional Cancer Center and National Cancer Center's Collaborative Cancer Conquest Promotion R&amp;D Project, entitled Development of monitoring cancer indicators and measurement by statistical analysis (Project Number: HA20C0004).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s11"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2022.912946/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2022.912946/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Statistics</surname><given-names>Korea</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Daejeon: Statistics Korea</article-title>. (<year>2020</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://kosis.kr" ext-link-type="uri">http://kosis.kr</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Won</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of cancer incidence and mortality in Korea, 2020</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res Treat.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4143/crt.2020.203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32178488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7176954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Cancer Institute</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Join <italic toggle="yes">Point Regression Program, V</italic>ersion 4.3.1</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Bethesda, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Cancer Institute</publisher-name> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>OECD</collab></person-group>. <source>Health at a Glance 2019: OECD Indicators</source>. (<year>2019</year>). <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>OECD Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pi&#241;eros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Znaor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mery</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A global cancer surveillance framework within non-communicable disease surveillance: making the case for population-based cancer registries</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Rev</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/epirev/mxx003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28472440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khare</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batist</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of performance indicators across a network of clinical cancer programs</article-title>. <source>Curr Oncol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3747/co.23.2789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27122972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4835013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng Yin Ling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sklavounos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Population-based quality indicators for end-of-life cancer care: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>JAMA Oncol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>142</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>150</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2019.3388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31647512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giuseppe La</surname><given-names>Torre</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alice</surname><given-names>Mannocci</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosario Andrea</surname><given-names>Cocchiara</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valeria</surname><given-names>D'Egidio</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cristina</surname><given-names>Sestili</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenza</surname><given-names>Lia</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sara</surname><given-names>Cianfanelli</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review of the Quality Indicators (QIs) to evaluate the CCCN approach in the management of oncologic patients</article-title>. <source>The Health Programme of the European Union</source>. (<year>2019</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ipaac.eu/res/file/outputs/wp10/quality-indicators-systematic-review-evaluation-comprehensive-cancer-care-network.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ipaac.eu/res/file/outputs/wp10/quality-indicators-systematic-review-evaluation-comprehensive-cancer-care-network.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arksey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Malley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Scoping studies: towards a methodological framework</article-title>. <source>Int J Soci Res Methodol: Theory Practice.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1364557032000119616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levac</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>PRISMA Extension for Scoping Reviews (PRISMA-ScR): checklist and explanation</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>169</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>473</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M18-0850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30178033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catto</surname><given-names>JWF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Efstathiou</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shariat</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quality indicators for bladder cancer services: a collaborative review</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eururo.2019.09.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31563501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Im</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Revision of quality indicators for the endoscopy quality improvement program of the national cancer screening program in Korea</article-title>. Clin Endosc. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5946/ce.2018.075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29874905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5997069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spitale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzucchelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bordoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>QC3 CRC Working Group. Quality indicators of clinical cancer care (QC3) in colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e002818</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2013-002818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23869102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3717445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazemi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghodoussipour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhanvadia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daneshmand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Socioeconomic and insurance status are independent prognostic indicators of higher disease stage and worse prognosis in bladder cancer</article-title>. <source>Urol Oncol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>784</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.urolonc.2019.04.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31076355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Carlos Eduardo Paiva, Talita Caroline de Oliveira Valentino, and Bianca Sakamoto Ribeiro Paiva</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of palliative care (PC) on aggressive end-of-life (EOL) care indicators among advanced cancer patients (ACPs)</article-title>. J Clin Oncol. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>34</volume> (<issue>Suppl. 15</issue>):<fpage>e21505</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2016.34.15_suppl.e21505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Partanen</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anttila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hein&#228;vaara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pankakoski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkeala</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bzhalava</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>NordScreen - an interactive tool for presenting cervical cancer screening indicators in the Nordic countries</article-title>. Acta Oncol. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1199</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>204</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0284186X.2019.1615637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31106635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altobelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rapacchietta</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marziliano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campagna</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Profeta</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fagnano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Differences in colorectal cancer surveillance epidemiology and screening in the WHO European Region</article-title>. <source>Oncol Lett.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>2531</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ol.2018.9851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30675315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6341797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sancho-Muriel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frasson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herv&#225;s</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flor-Lorente</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos Rodriguez</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero Sim&#243;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ANACO Study Group. Standard outcome indicators after colon cancer resection. Creation of a nomogram for autoevaluation</article-title>. <source>Cir Esp</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cireng.2016.10.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27916194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khare</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aprikian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blais</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brimo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quality indicators in the management of bladder cancer: a modified Delphi study</article-title>. <source>Urol Oncol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>328</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.urolonc.2016.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28065393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Won</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer statistics in Korea: incidence, mortality, Survival, and Prevalence in 2016</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res Treat.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4143/crt.2019.138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30913865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6473271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallion</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long Parma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Improving quality of life among latino cancer survivors: design of a randomized trial of patient navigation</article-title>. <source>Contemp Clin Trials.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cct.2018.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30399442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6463481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlayen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devriese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beirens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Eycken</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stordeur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quality indicators for testicular cancer: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1133</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2011.10.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22105018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koppert</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrancken Peeters</surname><given-names>MTFD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siesling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lingsma</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>From Multiple quality indicators of breast cancer care toward hospital variation of a summary measure</article-title>. <source>Value Health.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1200</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2020.05.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32940238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gac</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loaec</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silve</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaucel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Augereau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wernert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quality of advanced ovarian cancer surgery: a French assessment of ESGO quality indicators</article-title>. <source>Eur J Surg Oncol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>360</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejso.2020.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32863097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keikes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koopman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanis</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemmens</surname><given-names>VEPP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Punt</surname><given-names>CJA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Oijen</surname><given-names>MGH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluating the scientific basis of quality indicators in colorectal cancer care: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>166</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0959-8049(17)30255-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28988017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>ElNaggar</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hade</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Malley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Time to chemotherapy in ovarian cancer: compliance with ovarian cancer quality indicators at a national cancer institute-designated comprehensive cancer center</article-title>. <source>Gynecol Oncol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>151</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygyno.2018.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30282591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gooiker</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolfschoten</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastiaannet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van de Velde</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eddes</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Harst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dutch surgical colorectal audit group. Evaluating the validity of quality indicators for colorectal cancer care</article-title>. <source>J Surg Oncol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jso.23420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24115008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elfakir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chami Khazraji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zidouh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abousselham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Organization and evaluation of performance indicators of a breast cancer screening program in meknes-Tafilalt Region, Morocco</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>5153</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22034/APJCP.2016.17.12.5153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28124875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5454651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sampurno</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Stefano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuedea</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quality Indicators for global benchmarking of localized prostate cancer management</article-title>. <source>J Urol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>200</volume>:<fpage>319</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.juro.2018.02.071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29477721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katabuchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaneuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quality indicators for cervical cancer care in Japan</article-title>. <source>J Gynecol Oncol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>e83</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3802/jgo.2018.29.e83</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30207093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6189432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsiamis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baxi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Ieso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elsaleh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of quality indicators to monitor radiotherapy care for men with prostate cancer: a modified Delphi method</article-title>. <source>Radiother Oncol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>128</volume>:<fpage>308</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.radonc.2018.04.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29753551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chagpar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between adherence to National Comprehensive Cancer Network treatment guidelines and improved survival in patients with colon cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>119</volume>:<fpage>1593</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>601</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.27935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23280510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3889139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zullig</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zafar</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ordin</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gellad</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Using NCCN clinical practice guidelines in oncology to measure the quality of colorectal cancer care in the veterans health administration</article-title>. <source>J Natl Compr Canc Netw</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6004/jnccn.2013.0058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23584346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3712652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallbohmer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ploenes</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lurje</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of quality indicators following implementation of total mesorectal excision in primarily resected rectal cancer changed future management</article-title>. <source>Int J Colorectal Dis.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>903</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00384-011-1155-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21340717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann-Johnsen</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#229;resen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlichting</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naume</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyg&#229;rd</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Using clinical cancer registry data for estimation of quality indicators: results from the Norwegian breast cancer registry</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Inform.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>125</volume>:<fpage>102</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmedinf.2019.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30914174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baili</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoekstra-Weebers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hoof</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartsch</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Travado</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>EUROCHIP-3 working group on cancer rehabilitation. Cancer rehabilitation indicators for Europe</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1356</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2012.10.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23237740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Indicators and qualitative assessment of lung cancer management by Health Insurance Review and Assessment Service (HIRA) of Korea in 2015</article-title>. <source>Tuberc Respir Dis (Seoul)</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4046/trd.2017.0112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29332321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5771743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical responses and prognostic indicators of concurrent chemoradiation for non-small cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res Treat.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4143/crt.2011.43.1.32</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21509161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3072533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biganzoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marotti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cataliotti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cutuli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#252;hn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quality indicators in breast cancer care: an update from the EUSOMA working group</article-title>. <source>Eur J Cancer.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2017.08.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28963914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anfinan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sait</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Indicators of survival and prognostic factors in women treated for cervical cancer at a tertiary care center in Saudi Arabia</article-title>. <source>Ann Saudi Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5144/0256-4947.2020.25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32026705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7012029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrard</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Broad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Use of clinical quality indicators to improve lung cancer care in a regional/rural network of health services</article-title>. <source>Aust J Rural Health</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ajr.12493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30945777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nhung</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer mortality-to-incidence ratio as an indicator of cancer management outcomes in organization for economic cooperation and development countries</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Health</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>e2017006</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4178/epih.e2017006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28171715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5434228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rae</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pole</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Digout</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szwajcer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flanders</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>System performance measurement group. development of system performance indicators for adolescent and young adult cancer care and control in Canada</article-title>. <source>Value Health</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2019.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31952676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Factors analysis on the use of key quality indicators for narrowing the gap of quality of care of breast cancer</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1099</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-019-6334-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31718596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6852954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Which indicators of early cancer diagnosis from population-based data sources are associated with short-term mortality and survival?</article-title><source>Cancer Epidemiol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canep.2018.07.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30056051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6189520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cancer Guidelines and Reports Organization, Publication</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer Control and World Cancer Report IARC, 2009-2019</article-title>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.iarc.fr/research-groups-csu-rationale/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.iarc.fr/research-groups-csu-rationale/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Prevention &amp; screening / Reduce cancer risk / Can cancer be prevented? Canadian cancer Society-CANADA 2015-2019</collab></person-group>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cancer.ca/en/prevention-and-screening/reduce-cancer-risk/can-cancer-be-prevented/?region=on" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cancer.ca/en/prevention-and-screening/reduce-cancer-risk/can-cancer-be-prevented/?region=on</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European Guide for quality national Cancer Control Programs European Partnership for Action Against Cancer 2013-2019</collab></person-group>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.esmo.org/guidelines" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.esmo.org/guidelines</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://cancercontrol.eu/archived/uploads/images/European_Guide_for_Quality_National_Cancer_Control_Programmes_web.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://cancercontrol.eu/archived/uploads/images/European_Guide_for_Quality_National_Cancer_Control_Programmes_web.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National cancer care plan OECD 2013-2019</collab></person-group>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.oecd.org/els/health-systems/hcqi-cancer-care.htm" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.oecd.org/els/health-systems/hcqi-cancer-care.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quality</surname><given-names>Oncology Practice Initiative ASCO 2013-2019</given-names></name></person-group>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://practice.asco.org/quality-improvement/quality-programs/quality-oncology-practice-initiative" ext-link-type="uri">https://practice.asco.org/quality-improvement/quality-programs/quality-oncology-practice-initiative</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Scottish Cancer Task force National Cancer Quality Steering Group - Guidelines Indicators</collab></person-group>. <article-title>NHS: 2013&#8211;2020</article-title>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.gov.scot/publications/national-cancer-quality-steering-group/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gov.scot/publications/national-cancer-quality-steering-group/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO report on cancer: setting priorities investing wisely and providing care for all, WHO</collab></person-group>. <article-title>2005-2020</article-title>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/330745" ext-link-type="uri">https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/330745</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/nmh/ncd-tools/indicator14/en/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/nmh/ncd-tools/indicator14/en/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cancer statistics-2007-2020</collab></person-group>. <source>National Cancer Center (NCC) &#8211;Japan</source>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ncc.re.kr/cancerStatsList.ncc" ext-link-type="uri">https://ncc.re.kr/cancerStatsList.ncc</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cancer registration in Cancer national cancer center and cancer specialized Linked Hospital</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Japan National Cancer Information Service</article-title>. (<year>2019</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ganjoho.jp/data/reg_stat/statistics/brochure/2018_report.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://ganjoho.jp/data/reg_stat/statistics/brochure/2018_report.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hospital</surname><given-names>Cancer Registration 2010-2011 Five-Year Survival Rate Report</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Japan National Cancer Center, Cancer Information service</article-title>. (<year>2018</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ganjoho.jp/data/reg_stat/statistics/brochure/hosp_c_reg_surv_all_2010-2011.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://ganjoho.jp/data/reg_stat/statistics/brochure/hosp_c_reg_surv_all_2010-2011.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cancer</surname><given-names>Statistics 2019&#8211;2020</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Japan National Cancer Information Center</article-title>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ganjoho.jp/reg_stat/statistics/brochure/backnumber/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://ganjoho.jp/reg_stat/statistics/brochure/backnumber/index.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Japan National Cancer Center and Cancer Information service</collab></person-group>. <article-title>National Cancer Screening Status Data Book</article-title>. (<year>2019</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ganjoho.jp/en/professional/statistics/table_download.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://ganjoho.jp/en/professional/statistics/table_download.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cancer Incidence and prevalence Rate Report-2020</collab></person-group>. <article-title>National Cancer Registration, Japan Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare, Cancer Disease Management Division</article-title>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.mhlw.go.jp/content/10900000/000624853.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.mhlw.go.jp/content/10900000/000624853.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cancer Registration 3-year survival rate statistics-2013</collab></person-group>. <source>Japan National Cancer Information Service 2019</source>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ganjoho.jp/data/reg_stat/statistics/brochure/hosp_c_reg_surv_4_2013.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://ganjoho.jp/data/reg_stat/statistics/brochure/hosp_c_reg_surv_4_2013.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cancer statistics-2007-2020</collab></person-group>. <source>National Cancer Center (NCC) &#8211;Korea</source>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ncc.re.kr/main.ncc?uri=english/sub04_Statistics" ext-link-type="uri">https://ncc.re.kr/main.ncc?uri=english/sub04_Statistics</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Measures to improve the classification system of evaluation indicators related to medical quality</collab></person-group>. <source>Health Insurance Review and Assessment Service-2019</source>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.hira.or.kr/bbsDummy.do?pgmid=HIRAA020004000000&amp;brdScnBltNo=4&amp;brdBltNo=10773#none" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.hira.or.kr/bbsDummy.do?pgmid=HIRAA020004000000&amp;brdScnBltNo=4&amp;brdBltNo=10773#none</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Regional Health Index&#8722;2018</collab></person-group>. <source>Korea Health Promotion Institute. (Elio &amp; company)</source>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.healthranking.org/h_rslt_master.asp?menu_id=210" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.healthranking.org/h_rslt_master.asp?menu_id=210</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Regional Health Vulnerable Indicators-2016</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Korea Health Promotion Institute</article-title>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.khealth.or.kr/kps/publish/view?menuId=MENU00888&amp;page_no=B2017001&amp;pageNum=2&amp;siteId=&amp;srch_text=&amp;srch_cate=&amp;srch_type=&amp;str_clft_cd_list=&amp;str_clft_cd_type_list=&amp;board_idx=9176" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.khealth.or.kr/kps/publish/view?menuId=MENU00888&amp;page_no=B2017001&amp;pageNum=2&amp;siteId=&amp;srch_text=&amp;srch_cate=&amp;srch_type=&amp;str_clft_cd_list=&amp;str_clft_cd_type_list=&amp;board_idx=9176</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Health indicators-2013</collab></person-group>. <source>Hallym University, Community health Survey</source>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://chs.cdc.go.kr/chs/qt/qtMain.do" ext-link-type="uri">https://chs.cdc.go.kr/chs/qt/qtMain.do</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Community health Survey 2008-2019</collab></person-group>. <source>Center for Disease Control Korea</source>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://chs.cdc.go.kr/chs/qt/qtMain.do" ext-link-type="uri">https://chs.cdc.go.kr/chs/qt/qtMain.do</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spring</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pagoto</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Horn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fostering multiple healthy lifestyle behaviors for primary prevention of cancer</article-title>. <source>Am Psychol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0038806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25730716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4626078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Comprehensive Cancer Control Program (NCCCP) Making a Difference (2018)</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Available online at: www</article-title>.cdc.gov/cancer/ncccp</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donabedian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluating the quality of medical care</article-title>. <source>Milbank Mem Fund Q</source>. (<year>1966</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>166</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>206</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3348969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5338568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>